本字幕由志愿者义务贡献，采用许可协议
知识共享 署名-非商业性使用-相同方式共享 3.0 美国
Stanford University. >> Okay,
斯坦福大学
well welcome to lecture number three of Stanford CS193P,
欢迎参加斯坦福 CS193P 课程
fall of 2017 and 18 academic year.
2017 至 18 学年的第三节课
Today mostly, we're gonna talk about some Swift stuff.
今天，大部分时间我们将要讨论 Swift
Now, you've hopefully done your homework for the reading,
现在，希望你已经完成了你的阅读家庭作业
so some of the stuff will be kinda summary, but
所以这节课的一部分将会是总结那些内容
some of this is really not covered in the reading.
而这节课其他的并没有在阅读材料中涵盖
So I'm trying to give you the full picture of stuff,
所以我将试图给你展示这些内容的全貌
that reading is really great but it is great concise.
阅读材料是很棒的，但是它是非常简洁的
I know you probably feel like well,
我知道你可能会觉得
that was a lot of reading for something that's concise, but
要说它简明的话，内容是不是太多了
it is quite concise. So I'm gonna try and
但是它是非常简明的，所以我要尝试
cover some of the other stuff. But before I do all that,
涵盖一些其他的东西。在我开始之前
I'm gonna do a little, what I call a teaser demo of
我要做个简单的，我管它叫做 Auto Layout 的预告示例
Auto Layout where I'm gonna show you how we can make
在这里我将展示，在翻牌游戏中
our UI in concentration look good when we rotate the phone,
当我们旋转手机或者在不同尺寸的手机上运行程序的时候
or when we a run on little bit different sized iPhone, or
如何令我们的 UI 看起来很不错
whatever. I call it a teaser because I don't intend to
我把它叫做一个预告示例是因为我不想现在
teach you Auto Layout which is the feature that allows
教你 Auto Layout 的内容，虽然正是它才让我们
us to do that. It's just to show you what's possible.
能够这么做。这个示例仅仅是向你展示一些可能性
We'll actually have a whole lecture on auto
事实上我们会在三周后有完整的关于 Auto Layout
layout in about three weeks I think. But then,
的一堂课。除此之外
after I do that little demo, I'll be back. I'm first gonna
在做完那个小示例程序之后，我就会回归主题。我会
take just one minute to review what you should have
先用一小会儿时间复习你应该
learned by what we did last week and I'm literally just
在上周已经学会的内容，我会仅仅
gonna read it off a list with quick examples. And you can
照着列表过一遍，每条都有个简单的例子
kind of say in your head, oh yeah, yeah I got that,
你可以在心里默念，是的，是的我掌握了那条内容
I got that or oh wait, I did not really understand that and
我掌握了那条，噢等等，我并没有真的理解那条内容
that's a prompt to go back and look at it.
那会促使你返回去查看
Then we'll dive into this long list that you see up here,
之后我们会深入这个长长的列表，就是在这里你看到的这个
of various Swift things. So let's start with this demo I
上面有各种各样的 Swift 内容。让我们以这个我当时谈论的
was talking about, this Auto Layout demo.
Auto Layout 示例程序开始吧
What we're gonna do here, and I apologize for any technical
我提前为我们将要做的过程中会出现的任何技术
problems we have here because, actually, my computer died,
问题向你们道歉。因为实际上我的电脑死机了
and I had to put it. This is all brand new computer, so
所以我不得不用这台全新的电脑
I hope everything's installed properly. But here's the code,
我希望一切都安装好了。但这是我们的代码
I think, that we had at the end of the last lecture.
我们在上节课结束时的代码
And the UI looks pretty good. We laid it out.
我们布局的 UI 看起来很不错
But I just did this by dragging these things and
仅仅是通过拖拽这些东西并
using the little dash blue lines to put them
利用蓝色的虚线把它们放到了位
in position. And when we run this thing, it looks okay but
当我们运行它的时候看起来很不错
only on an iPhone X and
不过只是在 iPhone X
only in portrait mode like this. If I were to for
像这样竖屏的时候。但比如我
example, rotate this iPhone to the side which I can do
沿着侧边旋转这台 iPhone，我可以通过
in a simulator by going, Hardware, rotate left or
Simulator 菜单栏里的 Hardware > Rotate Left 或
right, you can see that my UI looks like this. My buttons
Right。你可以看到我的 UI 看起来是这样子。我的按钮
are kind of all jammed in the corner here. I've lost flips,
都挤在了这个角落里。我丢失了一些卡片
it's down here somewhere. I can't even see it.
它们在下面某个地方，甚至都看不见了
Still works, but it's kind of off in the middle of nowhere.
仍然可以工作，但都偏到不知道什么鬼地方去了
What we really want is for this UI to spread itself
我们真正想要的是让 UI 能够伸展开来
out and fill the whole space that's involved. By the way,
填满整个可用的空间。顺便说一下
you can also rotate your device with Command and
你可以用 Command 键和方向键来旋转设备
the arrows. Kind of a cool way to flip back and
这是用来旋转设备的比较酷的方式
forth. All right, so how are we gonna do that?
好的，接下来我们该如何做呢？
How are we gonna make our UI expand? Let's go ahead and
我们该如何让我们的 UI 展开？让我们
open up here, give ourselves some more space.
清理下工作环境，给自己更多的空间
And also I'm gonna zoom in a little so
我还想再放大一点让你们
you can see. Another thing I'm gonna do is we're gonna be
可以看到。我要做的另一件事情是我们将要
using these blue lines, the dashed blue
利用这些蓝色的线，这些当你移动组件的时候
line that appears as you move things around as part of this.
出现的虚线作为解决方案的一部分
So I'm gonna change my background from
我要将我的背景
to back to white temporarily, just so
暂时从黑色变成白色，仅仅是让
that we can see that those blue lines and
我们能够更好的看到那些蓝色的线
stuff a little bit better. So I'm just gonna go to white.
和组件。所以我设置成白色
When we come to run, I'll turn it back to black.
当我们运行的时候，我会改回黑色
So this is purely for dealing development issues here. So
这完全是为了方便开发而做的
it's really kinda two things I need to do to make this work.
为了让它能够工作，我需要做的是两件事情
One is, I need to kinda take all those buttons and
第一件事，我需要选中所有的按钮并
make them stick to the edges, right?
让它们粘在屏幕的边缘，对吧？
So that when they rotate and
这样子当它们旋转
the edges get longer and skinnier, they stick.
屏幕边缘变得更加细长，它们可以粘在上面
Right now, everything's stuck to the upper left corner.
现在，所有东西都堆在了左上角
The upper left corner, you're gonna find out next week,
你会在下周发现左上角
is the origin of drawing. In IOS where everything is kinda
是绘图的原点。在 iOS 里任何东西
stuck up to the upper left and then just, so
都会堆到左上角，所以
when we rotate it all, it just goes off the bottom,
当我们旋转整个屏幕的时候，界面会延伸到下方
we can't see it. So that's really what we need to do, but
导致我们没法看到它。所以那是我们需要做的事情
to stick them to the edges,
但要将按钮粘连到边缘
we also kind of need to group them together. Because when
我们先需要把它们组合在一起。因为当
the edges pull this group of 12 buttons apart,
边缘把这 12 个一组的按钮拉开的时候
they all need to kinda share that space.
它们需要分享这个空间
So there's two things we have to do.
所以这就是我们必须要做的两件事情
One is group them together, one is pin them to the edges.
一是把他们组合在一起，一是把它们钉在边缘上
So we're gonna do that with two different features in IOS.
我们将要用 iOS 中两个不同的特性来做这件事
One, the grouping things together,
其一，把按钮组合在一起
we're gonna do with stack view. Okay, so UI stack view
我们要用 stack view（栈）来做。UIStackView 是
is just another class in IOS like UI Button is a class and
iOS 中另一个类，就像 UIButton 是一个类
UI label is just another view in fact. And
UILabel 实际上也是个视图一样
what it does is it will take other views, like let's
它所做的就是将其他的视图，像这
say these four buttons and it will stack them together.
四个按钮，然后把它们堆叠在一起
Now, it only knows how to stack horizontally or
它只知道如何横向或竖向地堆叠
vertically. It can't stack 12 of these things in two
它不能直接将这 12 个按钮进行
dimensions like this. So I'm gonna have to make three
二维的排列，所以我不得不创建三个
horizontal stacks out of this group, out of this group, and
横向的栈，这些一组，这些一组
out of this group. But then I'll take those three stacks
这些一组。之后我再将这三个栈
and stack them vertically. Cuz it's perfectly fine to put
竖向地堆在一起。因为把栈放到栈里
stacks inside stacks, all right? And once I do that,
是完全可行的。一旦我这么做了
I'll have all 12 of these kinda stocked together. And
我将把全部的 12 个按钮都堆叠在了一起
then I can pin it to the edges and they'll stretch out. So
再钉到边缘，这些按钮就会自己分散开
how do we make this stack use?
我们该如何创建 stack view 呢？
Super simple, you just select it here. Let me zoom in so
非常简单，你仅需要选中这里。让我放大一点
we can really see what's going on here. We only need the top
方便看到正在发生什么。我们暂时仅需要
part for now. So I selected these four things.
顶端的部分。所以我选中了这四个按钮
I'm going down to this button right here.
我去到下面这里的这个按钮
You see this button, embed in stack?
你看到这个写着 Embed In Stack 的按钮了么？
Well, that's what it does. It embeds in stack.
没错，那就是它所做的事情：把东西嵌入栈中
And it embedded it. Now, couple of things.
它把这四个按钮嵌进去了，但有几个问题
One is, it made the buttons as small as it could when you put
一是 stack view 会让你放进去的按钮尽量地小
in the stack. It has 50 point font, remember, for
记得么按钮里那些 emoji 的字号是 50 点
those emojis. So that's just as small as they'll go.
所以这就是能放下这些表情符号的最小尺寸
It also has no spacing between. But I can put spacing
其次它们之间也没有空隙，但是我可以
in-between by just selecting it. It was left selected after
选中它并在给它加上。它现在是保持了我堆到一起后的
I stacked. And going over here to the inspector because this
选中状态。去到这里检查器，因为这个
stack view, just like a button, can be inspected,
UIStackView 就像按钮一样是可以被检查的
right? And you can see it made it horizontal,
你可以看到它自动是 Horizontal，横向堆叠
it kinda noticed my buttons were mostly horizontal. So
它注意到我的按钮大致是以横向分布的，所以
it picked horizontal. And so here's how I set the spacing.
选择了 Horizontal。然后这是我设置间隙的地方
I go down here. I'm gonna use a standard spacing.
我在下面选择标准间距，Use Standard Value
There's a lot of places when you're doing UI design where
当你进行 UI 设计的时候，有很多地方
you can pick an UI standard value and
你可以选择 UI 标准值
it'll pick a standard spacing.
它会选择一个标准间距
This is a standard spacing between buttons.
这就是按钮间的标准间距
And you wanna use that pretty much as much as possible.
你应该尽可能多的使用这个功能
That way, your UI will be spaced like other UI and
以这种方式，你的 UI 将像其他 UI 一样布局
you will feel like we are all on the same page as
这样你就会发现，我们和其他程序的 UI 设计师
UI designers across all these apps. Also I wanna make sure
达成了一种共识。我还想确保
that these four buttons get equal amount of space. Okay,
这四个按钮有着相同的间距
whatever space I am given here gets equally distributed and
无论这里给了多大的空间都能够均匀分布
I do that with this distribution thing here,
我通过这里的分布选项来做这件事
I say fill equally. Alignment just means I fill the whole
我选择均匀填满。Alignment Fill 意味着填满整个
space, I could have these things being centered or
空间，我本可以令这些东西居中或者
kinda pushed up to the top of the stack but
把它们推到栈的顶端
I'm gonna have it fill the whole space. So that's it.
但是我要把它填满整个空间。就这么简单
So I'm just gonna do the same thing with these two rows.
我要对这两行做相同的事情
So this one go down here, embed in stack,
选中这一行，点击下面的嵌入栈中
this group right here embed in stack. Oops,
这里这一组也嵌入栈中。不好
I did it twice there. Now I'm gonna select both of these.
我不小心点了两下。现在我同时选中这两个
Make them fill equally and standard value spacing. So
让它们均匀填满并且标准间距分布
now I've got three horizontal stacks. I'm gonna stack these
现在我得到了三个横向的栈。我要把它们堆叠
together, I'm gonna select them. By the way,
在一起，所以先选中它们。顺便说
dragging to select is really an awesome way to select.
拖拽选中真的是一种很酷的选中方式
I highly recommend you do that rather than trying to click on
我非常推荐你们这样做，而不是尝试点选
things. Because by the way, let's say I try to click on
因为比如说，我尝试点击这里
here to select this row. Oops, I selected the button inside.
来选择这一行。啊哦，我选中了里面的按钮
I didn't want that, I wanted the whole row. But
我并不想这么做，我想要这一整行。但是
if I just drag, not control drag but regular drag here,
如果我只是拖拽，正常的拖拽而不是按住 Control 键来拖拽
it selects the thing that I intercepted with my drag.
它会选中我拖拽截取的东西
Anyway, so I'm gonna select all three of these with drag.
总之，我会通过拖拽选中所有三个栈
And I'm gonna go embed in stack. You put them in
然后嵌入栈中。你把它们
a vertical stack. You notice this time it's vertical,
放到了一个竖向的栈中。你注意到这次它是竖向的
cuz it noticed those three things are vertical.
因为它注意到了这三个东西是竖向的
If your things are random,
如果你的东西是随机分布的
it'll pick the one that it thinks is the most likely.
它会选择一个它认为最可能的方向
You can always change it by going here and
你可以通过 Axis 这里来改变它
changing it to the other one. So we have vertical,
改成另一个。所以我们有了竖向排布
we also wanna fill equally, top to bottom here, and
我们还想要均匀填满，从上到下
we also want standard spacing. So
我们还想要标准间距
it's great. We got our buttons in this nice grid.
这太棒了。我们把按钮放置到了这个很好的栅格中
They're all Perfectly laid out in this rectangle. Now,
它们都完美地布局在了这个矩形中。现在
we want to pin this rectangle to the edges. Okay, so
我们想要把这个矩形固定到边缘上
that when the device rotates, or if the device was bigger,
那样当设备旋转的时候，或者如果设备更大的时候
like if it was an iPhone 8 Plus, or
比如它是一台 iPhone 8 Plus 或者
something like that and it was wider, so
更宽的设备
that it would all just stretch out. So, the way we do
以便它能够伸展开来。所以
that is first I'm going to use those dash blue lines.
我们要做的就是首先，我要利用这些蓝色的虚线
I picked up this thing. Again, picking it up,
我拖拽这个东西。再一次，要拖拽这个整体
you wanna select it first, then pick it up.
你需要先选中它，然后再拖拽
If you don't select it first and try to pick it up, oops,
如果你不先选中它，尝试去拖拽的话，阿哦
you might try and pull one of these things out of there.
你可能把其中一个东西拉出来
Okay? So, be careful about that. All right.
好么？所以，小心一点。好的
So, I'm gonna use the blue lines. I'm gonna
我要利用这些蓝色的线，我要
put this where it kinda suggests for
把它放置到它建议的
the upper left hand corner.
左上角的角落里
You see that? That's pretty much where the blue line,
你看到了它了么？那蓝线所在的地方
that would be the standard spacing from the edges.
就是和边缘有着标准的间距的地方
That's what the blue lines are telling you.
那就是蓝线正告诉你的东西
This is a standard place to put this. Now,
这是放置它的标准位置
I need to pin it and the way we make relationships between
我需要把它固定在这里。我们把 UI 里的视图
views in the UI like pinning them to each other and
关联起来的方式，比如让它们相互固定在一起
stuff is with control drag. Exact same way that we made
是通过按住 Control 键拖拽。和我们将 UI
a relationship between our UI and our code,
和代码关联起来的方式完全一样
by dragging the code, we do the same thing between views.
通过拖拽到代码里，我们也可以在视图间做相同的事情
So, I'm gonna control drag from this already selected
所以，我将要从选中的这里按住 Control 键拖拽
box here to the top. Okay, so I'm just dragging up towards
到顶部。好的，我向上拖拽到顶部
the top, and when I let go it's going to say, okay,
当我松开鼠标的时候，它会问
what relationship do you want between that view and
你想要视图和顶端用什么关系关联
the top. And there's various relationships you can have,
这里有各种关系你可以选择
like I said, in three weeks we're going to have
正如我说过，三周后我们将有
a whole lecture on these relationships, but
一整节课来讨论这些关系
at the very top is the one Top Space to Safe Area.
在最顶部的是 Top Space to Safe Area
You see that Top Space to Space Area? The safe area
你看到它了么？Safe Area（安全区域）
is a safe edge around the screen where you can
是一个安全的屏幕边缘，在那里你可以
safely draw without overlapping some other UI.
安全地绘制内容而不和其他 UI 重叠
So, here it's putting it right under the place where all
所以，在这里把它放在了所有的摄像头
the cameras and face recognition stuff is all in
面部识别模块等所有东西的下方
here. So, it's to keeping it below that. Now, if I had
所以，它是为避免被那些东西遮挡。如果我有
other UI on this, like tab bars, or title bars, or
其他 UI 在上面，比如 tab bar 或者 title bar
whatever, then the safety area would be inside those. So,
或其他任意东西，那么安全区域会在他们内部
we wouldn't overlap our titles and stuff. It's really cool.
所以我们不会和标题或其他东西重叠。这是非常棒的
So, I'm gonna put this top space little pin, so
这样我们就把它固定到了屏幕顶部
I'm kinda connected it and you can see this blue line appears
我把它连接了起来，你可以看到蓝色的线出现在
right here. Okay? This blue line here, long blue line.
这里，好么？这里的蓝色的线，这条长长的蓝色的线
It represents that pinning and I can even click on it. Okay,
它代表着那个关系，我甚至可以点击它
and when I click on it, look, it's inspectable in the top
当我点击它的时候，它变成了可被检查的
half here. Okay? And it's just telling me that I'm pinned
在这上半部分。好么？它就是告诉我
from the safe area top to the top of that stack view. And
栈视图的顶端固定到了安全区域的顶端
we're zero points away from it.
它们的之间的距离是 0 点
We wanna be right up against that safe edge.
我们就在安全区域的边缘上
That's where the blue dashed lines told me to put it, so
那里就是蓝色的虚线告诉我放置的地方，所以
that's where I'm gonna put it. Now, we can do the same thing
我就放置到了那里。现在我们可以对
to the left edge over here, so I'm gonna control drag over.
左边缘做相同的事情，按住 Control 拖到那里
This time it says, Leading Space to Safe Area.
这次它写着，到安全区域的前导间距
Now, why do you think that says leading instead of left?
现在，你认为为什么它写的是前而不是左呢？
Anyone wanna guess? It says leading instead of left,
有人想猜猜么？它写的是前而不是左
because some languages Hebrew, Arabic, they go right to
因为一些语言，比如希伯来语，阿拉伯语，它们是从右
left. The letters come from the right, and they flow
向左排列的。字母从右边来
out towards the left. In those cases, you want pretty much
流向左边。在那些例子里，你基本就是想要
your whole UI flipped over. So, you would want these
你的整个 UI 翻转过来。所以你会想要
buttons pinned to the other side, because the text on
这些按钮固定到另一边，因为按钮上的
the buttons is gonna be coming from the right. Okay?
文字是从右向左的，好么？
Now, it doesn't matter with our emojis, but
现在，对于 emoji 来说并不重要，但是
that's why we do leading and trailing instead of left and
这是为什么我们使用前导和后导而不是左和右
right. Okay? So, I'm gonna click this Leading Space to
的原因。好么？所以，我要点击这里的 Leading Space to
Safe Area right here. Connect it, I get another little blue
Safe Area。连接它，在这里我得到了另一个小的蓝色的
thing right here. You see this one? If I click on it,
东西。你看到这个了么？如果我点击它
it looks like a little I-beam,
它看起来就像一个“工”字
it's pinning these 2 and it's pinned it with 16 points.
它正关联着这两个，并且间距是 16 点
You see 16 points, evidently the blue lines think from
你看这是 16 点的距离。显然这些蓝色的线认为
the left edge, or the leading edge you want 16 points.
到左，或者前导边缘的距离，你想要的是 16 点
Okay, I'll take that. And then, of course,
好的，我会采用它。之后，当然
I could pin to the other side. Ctrl+drag over here.
我能够固定到另一边。按 Ctrl 拖拽到这里
And now, here I didn't use the blue line for that edge.
现在，在这里我没有利用蓝线来处理这个边缘
So, here if I say trailing space to safe area.
如果我选择到安全区域的后导间距
I get an I-beam, this huge, okay.
我得到了这个工字，但却非常的长
So, it goes all the way across like that.
几乎穿过了整个屏幕
And I don't want that, I want it to be the same as the other
但是我不想要这样子，我要它和其他边一样
side, 16 points. So, in my inspector right here,
16 点。所以在这里的检查器
this distance is this constant right here, 215 points.
这段距离，就是这里的 Constant 215 点
So, I'm gonna change that to be 16,
所以我要把它改成 16
so it matches the other side. Oh, and look what happened, it
所以它会和另一边匹配。噢，看发生了什么
pinned the edge of my buttons and they spread out, equally,
它固定了按钮的边缘，然后等距离伸展开来
filling equally, because we told we want to fill equally.
均匀填充起来，因为我们说过我们想要均匀的填满
Okay, so that's pretty cool, now we have the bottom.
好的，这是非常酷的。现在我还剩下底部
So, the bottom is a little trickier, because we've got
处理底部要麻烦一些，因为我们
flips down here. So, we want flips to be on the bottom, and
在底部有 Flips 标签。所以我们想要 Flips 处于底部并且
we want this thing to be above flips. So,
让这些按钮在 Flips 上方。所以
let's work on flips first, let's just get it, so
让我们先处理 Flips，好让
that flips is on the bottom and we're gonna do exact same
Flips 位于底部。我们要做的是一样的
thing. So, I'm gonna grab flips and use the blue lines,
所以我要拖拽 Flips，然后利用这些蓝色的线
okay, put it in the center on the bottom.
把它放到底部的中央
And then a controlled drag to the bottom,
然后按住 Ctrl 键拖拽到底部
and say that I want the bottom space to be pinned to the safe
选择固定到安全区域的底部间距
area. So, that's good. Now, when I did that,
所以，那是好的。现在，当我完成后
look I got this yellow and red lines and
看我得到了这条黄色和红色的线
I got a warning up here. See a warning this warning,
并且在这里我得到了一个警告。看这个警告
this means there is a warning and it can be red if you have
它意味着这里有一个警告，并且如果你有一个错误，它会是红色的
an error. And if you click on it it will tell you what all
并且如果你点击它，它会告诉你
your warnings are kind of a quick summary there, and
那些警告是什么，有一点像一个概要
here it says horizontal position is ambiguous for
这里它写到 Flip Count Label 的
your flip count label. In fact, it is ambiguous.
横向位置是模棱两可的。事实上，它是不确定的
I never told it where it horizontally,
我从没告诉过它在横向要位于哪里
I pinned it to the bottom, but
我把它固定在了底部，但是
I didn't say it was in the middle, or left, or
我没有告诉它是处于中央，还是左边，还是
right. Now I dragged it there with a blue lines, but
右边。我也没有用蓝色的线拖拽它
just dragging with blue lines, just put there, it doesn't pin it there. So
但这样只会把它放在哪里，并不会固定
really what I want with flips is,
所以我真正想要 Flips
I want it to be in the center. Okay, I want it to be in
我想要它位于中央。好的，我想要它位于
center. Just to show you something a little different.
中央。恰好给你们展示一些不一样的东西
And to do that, again, I Control+drag from flips right
为了做这件事，再一次的，我按住 Ctrl 键拖拽 Flips 标签到
here, to the thing I wanted to be in the center of,
这里，我想要它位于其中心的东西
which is this background here. So,
即这里的背景
I'm just gonna Control+drag to the background. And
所以我按住 Control 键拖拽到背景
another option is center this horizontally in the safe area.
另一个选项是在安全区域横向居中
So, I'm gonna do that. Now, it, it puts it in the middle.
所以我要这么做。现在，它居中了
It's still yellow here. So, what does this yellow say?
但它仍是黄色的。所以，这个黄色警告说了什么？
It says the frame for the Flip Count Label will be different
它说这个 Flip Count Label 的 frame
at run time. That's, because I have not constrained the size
在运行时将会不同。那是因为我还没有为标签的尺寸
of this Flip Count Label. I've let it be any size it wants.
添加约束。我让它可以是它想要的任意尺寸
And since it can be any size it wants,
正因为这样子
it's gonna want to be its natural size,
它将想变成它的自然尺寸
whatever size fits it.
能显示所有文字的大小
Now, I can fix this warning down here in this button right
现在，我能够在这里这个按钮，解决这个警告
here. This is where all your constraints.
这里是你所有的约束所在的地方
All this pinning things to edges is called constraints
所有这些把东西固定到边缘的东西叫做约束
we're constraining these views to be in a certain place,
我们将要约束这些视图到一个具体的位置
that we can just, um, actually we don't fix it there,
我们能够仅仅，呃...实际上我们不在这里处理
but we're gonna fix that over here.
但是我们要在这里解决
So, remember, our document outline that we had over here
所以记得，我们这里的的文件大纲
this little thing we hide. If you unhide that and
这个我们隐藏的小东西。如果你取消隐藏
look in the upper right, if there are any of these little
并且向右上方看，如果这里有任何的警告
warnings you have this little button, if you click on it,
你会得到这个按钮。如果你点击它
it will tell you all the problems. So,
它会告诉你所有的问题。所以
this one is a misplaced view, cuz this flip is too big. For
它是一个错误放置的视图，因为这个 Flips 标签太大了
what it should be. So, again, if you click on this little
相比自然尺寸而言的话。所以，如果你点击这个
triangle, it'll offer, hey, you wanna fix this? And
三角形，它会提供给你，嘿，你想要解决这个问题？
you can fix it by updating the frames, which we want,
你可以通过我们想要的更新 frame 来解决
cuz we don't care what the frame this is, the rectangle
因为我们并不关心它的 frame 是什么
that encloses it. It could be anything as long as it's
无论包含 label 的矩形是什么样的
pinned to the bottom and in the center. And we can
只要固定在底部的中央就好
do other things too, we'll talk about in a couple of weeks.
我们还可以做其他事情，那会在几周后讨论
So, I am just gonna update frame right here fix
所以，我选择 Update frames 来解决
missplacement. Look at moved flips down,
这个错位问题。看它把 Flips 标签向下移动了
it made the frame around it just barely contain it.
令它周围的框架刚好包含着它
Okay, and now they frame around that flip zero is it's
现在围绕在 Flip 标签周围的框架就是
natural size. If I run this and do a hundred flips, so
它的自然尺寸。如果我运行程序并且翻一百张牌的话
that it has to be bigger it will naturally get bigger.
如果它需要变大就能够自然地变大
Because it's size is not constrained.
因为它的尺寸并没有被约束
It's not pinned to anything, only its location. So,
除了位置之外是没有固定的
its size will get as big, or small it needs to to contain
所以它的尺寸会根据它所包含文字的大小
its stuff. And now, we see we have no Auto Layout issues.
来变大或变小。现在我们就没有了自动布局的问题
We have no warning up here, all is well. One last thing we
这里没有了警告，一切都正常。我们需要做的最后一件事是
need to do is the relationship between the top of the flips,
建立 Flips 标签顶部和
and the bottom of this. Now, I could just take this thing up
和按钮底部之间的关系。我可以选中上面的东西
here and control drag between that and the flips, right?,
按住 Control 键拖动到 Flips 标签，对吧？
that's a good idea. And we could, for example,
那是一个好主意。举个例子，我们可以
constrain the vertical spacing between the two, so I'm gonna
为两者间的垂直间距添加约束
click Vertical Spacing, there it is. It's this huge bar.
点击 Vertical Spacing 就可以了。但太长了
I could go over here and change it from 454 to 0, and
我可以去到这里把它从 454 改为 0
use all the space here. But that didn't look very good.
利用这里所有的空间。但是这看起来并不好看
I don't really like tall thin buttons like that.
我不太喜欢像这样子的高高瘦瘦的按钮
So I'm gonna leave this constraint in here. But I'm
所以我会把这个约束保留在这里
gonna change it from equal, where it has to be equal,
不过我要改变它，从原本的关系是等于
to 0 with the flips. Also I probably don't want 0, I want
和 Flips 零距离。可能我也不想要 0，我想要
a standard value here so I'm gonna change to standard value
一个标准值所以我要改成标准值
difference, okay, this, this, this distance.
好的，就是这段距离
And I don't it to be equal, I want it to be greater than or
我不想要它是等于，我想要大于等于
equal. So I just wanna make sure that these things on
我只是想要上方的这些东西
the top are always above the flips, greater than or equal.
总是在 Flips 标签上方，即大于等于
But it doesn't have to be right above it like that. So
但它们没有必要靠的太近
you don't have to always have these constraints be equal.
所以你没有必要总是把这些约束设定为等于
They can be greater than or equal, less than or
它们可以是大于等于，小于等于
equal kind of relative constraints. You see all this?
之类的现对约束。看到了么？
Now, we can run the app and this should all work.
现在，我们可以运行这个程序，它应该可以正常工作
Everything is kind of constrained to each other.
一切都互相约束
We can actually kinda take a look at it here in interface
实际上我们通过 Interface Builder 看一看
builder. Right, remember this button down here that showed
记得按下面这个按钮就会展示
us all these phones? We can say, okay, what's this thing
所有的手机么？我们可以看，它在
gonna look like on an iPhone 8? Here's iPhone 8,
iPhone 8 上看起来怎么样？这里是 iPhone 8
we click on it, and sometimes when it does it,
我们点击它，有时当你点击它的时候
you can kind of zoom in and out to get it to redraw.
你需要稍微放大和缩小来让它重新绘制
So this is what it's gonna look like on iPhone 8.
所以这就是它在 iPhone 8 上看起来的样子
We can look at, back on iPhone X, but rotate it.
我们返回查看在 iPhone X 上的效果，但是旋转它
So here's what it's gonna look like rotated on iPhone X,
这就是它在 iPhone X 旋转下的样子
that looks like that's gonna look okay. So
它看起来还不错
we can kind of preview a little bit what's going on
我们可以在 Interface Builder 中预览
here in interface builder, but there's no substitute for
会显示成什么样子，但并不能代替
running it. So let's just run it on our simulator and
实际运行程序查看。所以让我们在模拟器上运行它
see if it looks like what we expect.
看看它看起来是否和我们期待的一样
Right here it is, app seems to be working. Oh,
这就是了，应用看起来正在运行
let's go make our background black again. So go back here,
让我们把背景再次设为黑色。回到这里
background black, keep our Halloween theme intact.
背景为黑色，复原我们的万圣节主题
Right now here, okay, so this thing is working we can still
就是现在，应用正在运行我们仍然
match things, etc. But now when we rotate,
可以匹配卡片，等等，但是当我们旋转的时候
remember Command+Arrow, look, it re-lays out the entire UI
记得按住 Command 加方向键，看，它重新布局整个 UI
to fit the space. And it's doing this, it's relaying
来适应空间。它之所以在重新布局
it out because of those constraints we put it.
是因为我们放置的那些约束
We constrained this edge to be stuck to here,
我们约束这个边固定到这里
we constrained this edge to be stuck up here.
We constrained this distance to be
我们约束这段距离
greater than or equal to a standard distance.
大于等于标准距离
We constrained the bottom of this to be a distance down
我们约束它的底部到下面一段距离
here. We constrained the x position of this to be in
我们约束它的横坐标处在中央
the center. We put those constraints on here, and so
我们把这些约束放到这里
that when we flip this thing around, it's living with those
以便当我们旋转手机的时候，它能够和这些
constraints. Got it? So like I said, this is just a teaser
约束友好相处。明白了么？所以正如我说的
of this constraint stuff. It's a very powerful system for
它仅是这些约束的一个预告示例。约束是一个
doing these constraints and we'll talk all about that,
非常强大的系统，正如我说的
like I said, in about three weeks. Okay,
我们会在大约三个星期后详细讨论它
back to the slides. All right, so
回到幻灯片
here's your brief review of week 1, okay,
这里是第一周的一个简单回顾
hyperspeed review. Of course you know about target action,
超快速的回顾。你了解了目标操作
outlet out to out collection, outlet collections.
出口变量，出口变量集合
The card buttons, your flip count label. The touch card,
卡片按钮，你的计数标签，触摸卡片
you know about that. You learned all about methods and
你了解了它们。你学习了方法
properties, what their syntax was for all of those things.
和属性，它们的语法是什么
Properties like flip count and tons of methods all the ones
例如 flipCount 属性，还有
in concentration in card and view controller. You learned
ConcentrationCardViewController 里所有的方法
about property observing right when the flip count changed,
你学习了属性观察，当 flipCount 改变的时候
we have that didSet that would cause the UI to change as
我们有 didSet，它可以导致 UI 也发生变化
well. You obviously learned about arrays,
显然你学习了数组
how to put things in arrays, how to declare an array.
如何把东西放到数组里，如何声明一个数组
You learned a ton about model view controller.
你学会了关于 MVC 的很多知识
We went and made the Concentration game have
我们令翻牌游戏拥有了一个模型
a model like concentration on the card.
像基于 Card 的 Concentration 文件
You learned about value types versus reference types, right?
你学习了值类型和引用类型，对吧？
The card, which is a struct, a value type that gets copied
Card，它是一个结构体，一个值类型，当你把它丢到其他地方
when you throw it around. So when we put them in the array
它会被拷贝。所以当我们把它们放到数组里时
there, we made the copy by just putting it in twice.
我们通过放置两次来完成这次拷贝的操作
And they copied it each time you put it in there,
并且每次你把它放到那里都会拷贝
remember that? You learned about initializers,
记得么？你学习了构造器
we had initializers both for Card
我们添加了构造器到 Card
and for Concentration
和 Concentration
they each did different things to get
它们每个都做了不同的事情来
themselves an initializer. We didn't do initializer for
让自己被初始化。我们并没有给 UIViewController 实现构造器
our UI view controller and we probably never will.
而且我们大概永远都不会这么做
UI view controllers initialization is messy. Okay,
UIViewController 的构造过程是混乱的
so we try at all possible not to use init for our view
所以我们尝试尽可能地不使用视图控制器
controller. And I explained that in your homework
的 init 方法。我在你们的家庭作业里解释了这件事
that's going out today, you can read about it. You learned
它会在今天发布，你们可以阅读相关内容。你们学习了
about static methods like get unique identifier, static
关于静态方法的知识，比如获取唯一识别码的方法，还有静态
vars like the identifier factory that we've created
变量，比如我们创建的识别码工厂
there. You learned about lazy properties like game, which
你们学习了惰性属性，比如 game 变量
depended on another property, and so it couldn't initialize.
它依赖于另一个属性，所以它不能被初始化
We just made it lazy so that it wouldn't actually
我们通过懒加载它，所以
initialize until someone asked for it,
直到需要的时候才会被初始化
which would of course be after the thing is all initialized.
当然这只可能在实例初始化之后才会发生
You learned about for in loops, which in Swift only
你们学习了 for 循环，它在 Swift 中
work by iterating over what's called a sequence.
只能用来迭代序列
And we learned that countable range is a sequence, right?
我们学习的 CountableRange 是一个序列，对吧？
0..< than whatever is a countable range,
0..< 是一个 CountableRange
that's a sequence. But also array is a sequence,
它是一个序列。而且数组也是一个序列
and string is a sequence of characters.
String 是字符的序列
A lot of things are sequences, you can for in over them.
很多事物都是序列，你可以对它们进行 for 循环
We're gonna talk about what it means to be a sequence
之后我们将会讨论成为一个序列意味着什么
little later, probably on Wednesday. You learned about
大概是在周三。你们学习了
dictionary. Of course our emoji were in a dictionary.
字典，当然我们的 emoji 是在一个字典里
We learned about type conversion.
我们学习了类型转换
We convert types by creating a new thing. And using an init
我们通过创建一个新的事物来转换类型。比如
with the old thing like uint 32 of an int makes a uint,
通过一个 UInt32 的 init 方法，那么这个 UInt32
convert into a uint 32. And of course, you learned a lot
就是一个 Int 转变而来的。 当然，你们学习了很多
about optionals which I'm sure are all still new to you and
关于可选类型，只是我确定它对你们来说还十分陌生
I'm gonna talk a lot today about optionals and how they
我会在今天讨论很多关于可选类型的内容，它们是如何
really work. And what's really going on with optionals, okay?
工作的，到底发生了什么，好么？
So that's your review of week one.
这就是你们第一周的回顾
If for some of these, if you don't feel like you understand
如果你感到你还没明白这些内容
these, probably haven't done your homework yet, then you
你可能还没有做完家庭作业
won't understand this, very important. Okay, the first two
所以你不理解它。都是非常重要的。好的
things I'm gonna talk about here are just a little quick
首先，我要讨论的两个事情
minor things, asides. I mentioned doing a for
小事。我提到过用浮点数
loop over floats. So this for i = 0.5, i < 15.25 whatever,
做 for 循环。比如 for i = 0.5; i < 15.25
that's something you might see in C. You can't do that
这是你可能会在 C 语言中看到的东西，你不可以
in Swift, okay? Swift doesn't have, it only has for in,
在 Swift 中这么做，好么？Swift 只有 for in
that's all it has. But how do we create a countable range or
这是它拥有的全部。但是我们该如何创建一个 CountableRange 或者
some kind of sequence of those floats because 0.5...15.25,
类似的浮点数序列？因为 0.5...15.25
that's actually legal to say, but
事实上这么说是合法的，但是
that's only a range in Swift not a countable range. And
在 Swift 中它只是一个 Range 而不是 CountableRange
that's because we don't know what to count by there,
这是因为我们不知道间隔数是多少
so it can't create a countable range. So
所以它没办法创建一个 CountableRange
the way we do that is using a global function called stride.
我们实现它的方法就是使用一个叫做 stride 的全局函数
Stride has form, through or from and
stride 有 from:through: 或者 from:to:
to depending on whether you are gonna include the last
两种形式，取决于是否要包含区间的上限
thing, and a by tells you what it strides by. Stride is
最后一个 by 告诉你每一步的跨度是多少。stride
function that creates a countable range. Countable
是一个创建 CountableRange 的函数
range is a generic type like array is a generic type.
CountableRange 是一个泛型，正如数组是一个泛型
It can count over not just ints,
它不仅能够在整数间计数
it could count over floats, it could even count over indexes
还能够计数浮点数，它甚至可以计数
into a string, all kinds of things it can count over.
字符串的索引，所有种类的事物它都可以计数
And this stride knows how to create a countable range,
stride 了解如何创建一个 CountableRange
in this case a closed countable range because I did
在这个例子里是一个 ClosedCountableRange 因为
through 15.25, not to 15.25.
我写的是 through: 15.25 而不是 to: 15.25
It creates one that goes over floats and knows to step by
它创建了一个浮点数闭区间，以 0.3 为跨度
three, 0.3 there. So that's how you do floating point.
看这里的 0.3。所以这就是处理浮点数的方法
And you don't have to do that for your homework or anything,
家庭作业里用不到这个
but I just wanted to be complete about how we do
我只是想要完整的讲述我们该如何处理
a countable range for floats. All right, tuples.
浮点数的 CountableRange。元组
I try to fit everything into Concentration that I can,
我尽力尝试把一切都纳入 Concentration 中去
an example of everything. But I couldn't figure out
一个包含一切的例子，但是我没法想出
how to fit a tuple in even though tuple is a very simple
如何把元组融入进去，即使元组是一个非常
little data structure. And all that tuple is, essentially,,
简单的数据结构。元组基本上
like a mini struct that has no methods or vars or anything.
就像一个没有方法或变量的迷你结构体
Just has values in it. So it's kind of like struct in other
在里面只有值，所以它有点像其他语言中的结构体
languages, like C structs. They don't have methods or
比如 C 语言结构体。它们没有方法
vars or anything, or they kind of have vars,
变量或其他东西，或者说它们在某种程度上拥有变量
they have the data stores and that's it.
它们有储存的数据，但也就那样了
So but the tuple is super lightweight and
但是元组是非常轻量的
you kinda define everything in line.
所有的都能在一行里定义
So here's what a tuple looks like. Here's a tuple x. x,
这是一个元组看起来的样子。这是一个元组 x
is up here, is of type tuple. And this tuple has three
x 的类型是元组。这个元组里有三个
things in it. A string, an int, and a double. And
部分。一个 String，一个 Int，一个 Double
I set its value by just saying equals parentheses,
通过 = (三个值)
the three things, okay, the three values. Now, what's
来给它赋值。关于元组
kinda cool about a tuple, as a lightweight struct kinda
一个轻量的数据结构来说，非常酷的事情是
thing, is that the names of the elements is very flexible.
其元素的名称是可变通的
You can define the names when you get the values, like this,
你能够在当你获得值的时候定义名称，像这样子
let parentheses word number value equal x. And
let (word, number, value) = x
that actually assigns each of the values of x to the three
那就能够把 x 的每个值都赋给了
variables word, number and value. Okay? So I'm kind of
word，number，value 三个变量，好么？
giving these struct elements names as I grab them out, or
有点像当我揪出这些元素的时候给了它们名字
we can do the other way around. When I define x,
或者我们可以用另一种方式来做。当我定义 x 的时候
I can say x is a tuple that has a string and
我可以写 x 这个元组有着 String
Int and double called w i and v. Then,
Int 和 Double，它们分别称为 w、i 和 v
when I have x in my hands, I can get w,
当我使用 x 的时候，我可以通过
i and v with using, using this dot notation,
使用点语法来获得 w、i 和 v 的值
kind of like it's a var almost in a struct, x.w, x.i, x.v.
它有点像是一个结构体中的变量，x.w，x.i，x.v
See, so now I'm declaring the names when I declare
所以我可以在声明变量的时候就选好名称
the thing. But, and even if you do this, you can still
但是即使你这么做，你仍可以
redeclare the names to be something else by saying, let
重新声明这些名字，通过写
word num val = x, it'll crate those three local variables so
let (word, num, val) = x 就会创建三个局部变量
super flexible on the naming of those three things.
所以这三个事物的命名是可以变通的
Usually when we crate a tuple we want to use the second way
通常当我们创建一个元组的时候，我们想要用第二种方法
the x : i : v way although we probably would not use x,
x: i: v:，即使我们可能不会使用 x
i and v those are terrible names that is just my
i 和 v，这些是糟糕的名字，那是因为
slide only has so much space.
我的幻灯片横向的只有这么多空间
Horizontally, probably word, number or
大概 word、number 和 value
value would have been better names. Usually we do that, and
会是更好的名字。通常我们这样做
that's mostly because of documentation,
是为了方便写文档
we want people to know what those three things are. If we
我们想要人们了解那三个东西是什么
just declare it like x at the very top there, string, int,
如果我们仅仅声明它，像上面的那个 x 那样，String，Int
double, people are like, hm, what are those three things?
Double，人们会说，这些东西到底是什么？
So, what's a tuple good for? Well,
所以，元组的优点是什么？
it's good any time you wanna group some stuff together
它适合用来把一些事物组织在一起
that's really lightweight, it doesn't have any methods or
它是非常轻量的，它没有任何方法或者
anything associated with it. It's also very good for
关联的东西。同时它对于
returning multiple values from a function. A function of
返回多个值的函数来说也是非常好的
Swift can only return a single thing, but
Swift 的函数只能返回一个单独的事物
that thing could be a tuple, and now you can return as many
但是它可以是一个元组。用元组就可以想返回多少
things as you want, okay? So if I had a function getSize,
就返回多少事物，好么？所以如果我有一个函数 getSize
get's a person's size, their height and their weight.
获得一个人的尺寸：身高和体重
Let's say I can return a tuple with weight and height, and
我可以返回一个包含体重和身高的元组
so when I got it back I just x.weight or
所以当我得到返回值的时候，我只需要 x.weight
even just getSize().weight or getSize().height, access
甚至只需要 getSize().weight 或者 getSize().height
it directly. So that's what tuples, is I didn't make you
直接获取它。所以这就是元组，我没有在你们的
read about it tuple in your first reading assignment but
第一个阅读作业中让你们阅读元组
you'll be reading about it in your next one.
但是你会在下一个作业里阅读它的内容
it's very simple, it's exactly what it seems,
它是非常简单的，它完全是它看起来的样子
there's nothing magical here, there's no hidden things, it's
这里没有魔法，没有隐藏的内容
just a simple little struct, yeah? Sorry? Do they support
它就是一个简单的小结构。抱歉？>> 它们支持索引么？
indexing? Do tuples support indexing, you mean like,
>> 元组支持索引么，你的意思是，像
get thing number 1, or get thing number 2? Not really,
得到第一个元素，第二个元素？并不
and we wouldn't really wanna do it that way. If we really
我们也不想要用这种方式做。如果我们真的
had something we'd index, we'd wanna use an array there,
需要被索引的事物，我们会在那里使用一个数组
because, you know what I'm saying? It would obfuscate
因为，你懂得，它会混淆
what's going on. The whole great thing about tuples,
我们用的究竟是什么。元组美妙的地方在于
you can name each one and let people know what they are, so.
你可以命名每一个元素让人们知道它们是什么，所以你懂的
All right, now, okay, that was it for
好的，这就是那些小知识
little things, now we're back to something very important.
现在我们返回一些非常重要的事情
This is a big thing. This is computed properties.
这是一个重要的事情：计算属性
So all the properties that you saw in Concentration,
你在 Concentration 中看到的所有属性
were stored properties. They were just normal vars
都是存储属性。它们就是正常的变量
like you're used to in another languages, right?
就像你在其他语言中用的那些一样，好么？
Like this var foo: Double, that's a double precision
像这个变量 foo: Double，它是一个双精度
floating point number, and it's just stored in memory.
浮点数，它只是储存在内存中
It's stored with whatever struct or class it's part of.
它储存在任何它属于的结构体或类里面
But it is possible to declare foo like this,
但是也可以像这样子声明 foo
foo Double open curly brace, get with the curly brace, set,
for: Double
with some curly brace
set {} }
In that case, foo is never stored anywhere, instead,
在这个例子中，foo 从没有被储存，相反
every time someone asks for
每次人们请求 foo 的时候
foo, it gets calculated with the code inside get. And
它被 get 中的代码所计算
every time someone sets the value of foo,
每次人们设置 foo 的值
this code that's in here inside set gets executed.
在 set 里面的代码得到执行
Okay, so I got a little pointer here. So
好的，我现在用这个小的指示器
this code gets executed when you set, this code up here
当你设置 foo 的值时，这行代码得到执行。上面
gets executed when you get. Instead of it being stored
这行代码当你获取 foo 的值时执行，而不是被储存
somewhere. Now, the set by the way, that set(newValue) part,
在某个地方。顺便说一下，set(newValue) 部分
that's optional. So you can have computed properties
不是必须的。所以你可以拥有只有 get 部分的
that are only get, call those read only computed properties.
计算属性，我们称之为只读计算属性
You can't have ones that are only set,
你无法拥有只有 set 的计算属性
you can have get only but not set only.
你可以只拥有 get 但不能只拥有 set
If you have set only make a function set whatever.
如果你要只拥有 set，那就做成一个 setXXX 方法
You wouldn't use a var like that. Okay, so why a computed
你不会像那样子使用一个变量。所以为什么计算属性
properties important? What do you use them for?
如此重要？我们用它来做什么？
Well, a lot of times you have something that is perceived as
很多时候，你有一些东西被看作
a property of your struct or class that actually is derived
结构体或者类的属性，但其实
from other state inside of your struct. And when you have
基于其他状态演变而来的。这时
that situation, you do not want to have a stored property
你不希望拥有一个存储属性
because you don't want to have the same
因为你不想在两个不同的变量里
information in two different vars. Because they can get
储存着相同的信息。因为它们会
out of sync, all kinds of problems happens, so
失去同步，还有各种各样的问题发生
you one way or the other wants to derive itself
你的某一个变量会想从另一个中推导出自身
from the other one. Here's an incredibly good example
这里是一个非常好的例子
indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard in concentration.
Concentration 中的 indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
That is easily derived by looking at the cards. So
它可以轻松的通过观察卡片得到
you really, we'll really kind of bad to have made that
所以让它成为一个寄存属性对我们来说是不太好的
a stored property, becauase we have to keep that thing
因为我们不得不保持它完全
exactly in sync with the face up state of all the cards.
与所有卡片正面朝上的状态同步
That's really error prone way to design. So, we could
那是一个非常糟糕的设计方式。所以我们可以试着
imagine doing, implementing indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard as
想象实现 indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
computed property
为计算属性
with the get just looks at all the cards. And if you'll
它的 get 只需要查看所有的卡片。如果你
only find one FaceUpCard it returns that index, otherwise
只发现一张正面向上的卡片，就返回那个索引，否则
it it returns nil. And the set just looked to that index,
它返回 nil。set 只需要查看那个索引
make sure that card face up and all the rest will face
确认那张卡片为正面朝上而其他卡片正面朝下
down, you see? So, we're just using this computed property
看到了么？本质上我们正使用这个计算属性
to essentially provide this conceptual property,
来提供这个只是概念上的属性
which is the indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard,
也就是唯一向上的卡片的索引
that is the property of our game, but
它是我们游戏的一个属性
it's computed from the other one. Everyone get what
但是它从另一个属性演算而来。所有人都
I'm saying there? Okay, so let's go to Concentration and
理解我在说什么么？好的，让我们去到 Concentration
make this change, see what this would look like
进行这个修改，看看如果使用一个计算属性的话
if you used a computed property here like we
它会是什么样子，好么？
should've in the first place, all right?
起初我们本应就这么做
So let's go back here to Xcode,
我们回到 Xcode
here we go bring our code back up, get rid of that.
把我们的代码拿回来，隐藏这个
Let's go, oops, let's go to concentration, that's where
让我们去到 Concentration，我们代码所在
this is all right? So everyone recognize this code, right?
的地方，好么？大家都还认得到这些代码么？
This is our entire concentration,
这是我们完整的 Concentration
pretty efficient code as is but it's actually gonna look
已经是足够有效率的代码了，但是它会看起来更好
even better once we do this as you'll see. So we're here,
一旦我们实现这个功能，你马上就会看到
we have index of one and only FaceUpCard. So
我们有 indexOfOneAndOnyFaceUpCard
I'm gonna make it computed by putting these curly braces in,
我要把它写成计算属性，通过放置这些大括号
as soon as I do that, now it's a computed property. Actually,
我一完成它，它就变成了一个计算属性
before we do that, let me show you even simpler case of this
事实上，在我们做之前，让我给你们展示一个更简单的例子
just to kinda get you warmed up on computed property.
仅仅是让你们熟悉一下计算属性
Sometimes, you have just a simple calculation like this.
有时候，你有一个像这样子的简单计算
The number of pairs of cards which are calculated from
numberOfPairsOfCard，它由 cardButtons
the card buttons, all right? There might be other times
计算出来。可能在我们的 ViewController 里还有其他时候
inside our view controller, we wanna know this number,
我们想要知道这个数字
how many pairs of cards do we have. So
我们拥有多少对卡片。所以
that's kind of a property and is derived from this data. So
它是一种属性，并且通过这个数据推导出来
I'm gonna take this out of here and
所以我要把它拿出来而且
have number of pairs of cards be a property.
把 numberOfPairsOfCard 写成一个属性
It's gonna be a new var numberOfPairsOfCards, and
它会是一个新的变量 numberOfPairsOfCard
it's gonna be of type Int, and it's gonna be computed, so
它的类型是 Int，它是一个计算属性
I'm gonna have a get. It's gonna be read only, so
我会拥有一个 get，它会是只读的，所以
I'm gonna return this. It's not gonna have a set,
我会返回这个，它不会有一个 set
there's no, there's not gonna be any set right here. And
这里不会有任何的 set
voila I've created a simple computed property that's read
我已经创建一个简单的只读的计算属性
only. By the way if you have a read only property,
顺便说如果你有一个只读属性
you do not actually have to have the word get there. So
实际上你不必须在这里写 get 关键字
a read only property
所以一个只读属性
can look like that. Only if you only have a get,
可以是这个样子。你仅有一个 get 的时候可以这么做
if you have a set can't do that. So this is a super
如果你有一个 set 不能这么做。所以这是一个非常
simple little one. So now let's go back over here and
简单的计算属性。现在让我们返回这里
do the little more complicated one over here.
完成这个稍微复杂的计算属性
This one does have a get and it also has a set. And
这个属性既有一个 get 也有一个 set
set right here, I put in the slide that has newValue.
set 就在这里，我放到幻灯片里的那个有一个 newValue
This is just gonna be the local variable inside here
这只是里面一个局部变量
that contains the new value that someone set,
包含着某个人设置的新
indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard to. A lot of times we don't
indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard。大部分时候
put anything there, if you do that,
我们在这里不放任何东西，如果你这么做了
it defaults to newValue. That's the name of the locals,
它的默认值就是 newValue。它是那个局部变量的名字
there's a special variable in here called newValue.
这里有一个特殊的变量叫做 newValue
But if you wanted to call it something like index,
但是如果你想称呼它，比如 index
you could do that, it's totally up to you,
你可以那么做，这完全取决于你
a lot of times we just say use newValue though. Okay,
不过大部分时候我们直接使用 newValue
so getting the index what do we have to do
至于获取 index 的值，我们必须这么做
to calculate the index of faceup card. So I'm just gonna
来计算正面朝上卡片的索引。我要
write the little code and have a little localvariable,
写一小段代码，得到一个局部变量
say foundIndex which is gonna be an optional Int. So
叫做 foundIndex，它会是一个可选类型的 Int
I'm gonna look through all the face cards and
我会遍历所有的卡片
see if I can find one that's gonna be the one I found.
查看是否能找到我翻开的那张卡片
So I'm gonna use a for loop here
所以我要使用一个 for 循环
go through all the cards.indicises, all right?
遍历所有的 cards.indices
I'm gonna look at each card, and if that card is FaceUp.
我会查看每一张卡牌，如果那张卡牌是正面朝上的
So I found the FaceUp card, whoo-hoo.
我就找到了它
I'm gonna say, if foundOne is nil, in other words,
如果 foundOne 是 nil，换句话说
I haven't found the card yet and this is my first one.
我还没找到那张卡片，也就是这是第一个正面朝上的
Then I'm gonna set not foundOne, what is it called,
不是 foundOne，它被叫做
foundIndex = index, all right? So here I'm just saying if I
foundIndex = index，好么？所以这里我写的是
just found my first one let's remember it.
如果我找到了我的第一张卡片，让我们记住它
Otherwise, if foundIndex is not nil that means this is
否则，如果 foundIndex 不是 nil，它意味着
the second FaceUpCard that I found.
这是我找到的第二张正面朝上的卡片
Cuz I already found one and I found another one, so
因为我已经找到了一张并且找到了另一张
here I am just gonna to return nil. Because if there's two
所以这里我会返回 nil。因为如果这里有两张
FaceUpCards then obviously the index of the one and
正面朝上的卡片，那么显然 indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
only FaceUpCard is nil, there's no such thing. And
是 nil，没有这样的东西
if I make it all the way through this for
如果我完成了整个 for 循环
loop I'm just gonna return the foundIndex, which is either
我会返回 foundIndex，它要么
going to have been set to the one card I found or
被设定成了我找到的那张卡片或者
it'll still be nil from this declaration.
仍然是 nil，通过这个声明来说的话
Remember that optionals always get
还记得可选类型在声明的时候总是自动
this free equals nil when they're declared, right? So it
获得这个缺省值，对吧？所以
starts out nil and if I never found one, it'll still be nil,
它以 nil 开始，如果我没有找到一张卡片，它将仍是 nil
which is right cuz that means there'll be no FaceUpCards.
这是正确的，因为它意味着这里没有正面朝上的卡片
We're gonna understand this simple code right here,
我们都理解这里的这块简单的代码
how about the set case? On the set case,
至于 set 的情况呢？在 set 例子中
I'm just gonna loop through all the cards and
我要遍历所有的卡片
turn all face down except for this one that they just set it
把它们全部翻到背面，除了这张，它刚刚
to, which is gonna be new value, all right? So I'm just
被设置成了 newValue，对么？
gonna go through my cards for index in cards.indices.
我要遍历我的卡片，for index in cards.indices
Great way to go iterate through this countable
这是一个很棒的方式来迭代这个包含
range of all the indexes in my array. I'm gonna say,
数组里所有索引的 CountableRange。我会写
cards.index.isFaceUp = false,
cards.index.isFaceUp = false
for most cards. But in case the index here,
对于大部分卡片来说。但是对于这个索引来说
this index equals the new value of this, then I'm gonna
如果它等于 newValue
set it to true. Okay, so here this is an expression
我把它设置为 true。好的，这是一个表达式
that's true if someone said indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
如果某个人说 indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard 等于
equals whatever. If this is the whatever they said,
无论什么 ，如果这是那个值的话
then we're gonna have this be true if the card's face up,
那么我们会让正面朝上的它是 true
o therwise this will always be false. Everybody got this
否则它会一直是 false。每个人都理解了
little code right there? Come through with that? All right,
这一小段代码么？能够理解它么？好的
that's it. Okay, now the indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
这就是它了。现在 indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
is computed like this,
就像这样子被计算了
from the card, we do not need to take responsibility for
我们没有必要负责去做一些像
doing things like setting it to nil here. This is the case
把它设为 nil 之类的事情。这是一个例子
where we found two cards, we got two cards that we're
在这里我们找到了两张卡片，我们有两张要尝试匹配
trying to match, well, obviously there's two cards.
的卡片，很明显这里是两张卡片
So we had to set the indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
所以我们不得不设置 indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
to nil cuz there were two. But we don't have to do that
为 nil 因为这里有两张。但是我们现在再也不必这么做了
anymore, because it's always computing that,
因为它总是会计算它的值
every time we ask, it goes and looks at the card. And
每一次我们请求，它去到程序里查看卡片
even better than that is this case down here. Okay,
比这更好的是下面这个例子
this case down here, we are setting the
下面这个例子里，我们正在设置
indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceupCard to
indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard 为
be the index. That's because this was the case where there
index。那是因为在这种情况下
were already two or there were none,
已经有了两张卡片或者没有卡片正面朝上
and now we turn those faceDown and do this new one.
我们把它们翻转朝下然后进行新的选择
So we're already setting this and it does all of this.
我们已经设置过它了，程序做了所有的事情
Setting this thing to something already turns all
设置它为某个值已经把所有其他的卡片
the other cards faceDown. And already sets that card faceUp,
翻到了背面。而且已经设置那张卡片朝上
so we don't need any of that code. So you see how making
所以我们不需要这里任何的代码。所以你看
the computed property makes this code much simpler and
计算属性令我们的代码多么的简单易懂
straightforward. Cuz it really gets at the heart of what's
因为它完全囊括了正在发生的事情的核心
going on. I'm just setting the indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
我只需要设置 indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard 的值
to this index
为这个 index
that I just clicked on or
我点击的 index
I'm just turning this card faceUp. And the next time
把这张卡片翻到正面。下一次某人
someone asks for the indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
请求 indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard 的时候
it's gonna do the right thing, right?
它就会是正确的值，对吧？
So let's go and run, make sure we didn't break
让我们运行程序，确保我们在把它创建成一个计算属性
anything making this into a computed property. Here we go,
过程中没有改坏任何东西。让我们开始吧
hopefully we can still match, yeap, that matches,
希望我们仍然可以匹配，好的，它匹配了
and the matching is working, and the mismatching is also
匹配正在工作，不匹配也
working. Really cool computed properties,
是好的。计算属性真的很酷
you're gonna see computed properties everywhere in iOS,
你将会在 iOS 的每个地方看到计算属性的身影
they get very common, yeah. >> [INAUDIBLE]
它们是非常常见的 >> [学生提问]
>> Okay great question, so
>> 好的，非常棒的问题。所以
when would I ever use this var versus
什么时候我会使用这个变量而不是
having two methods, one which get's the index and
用两个方法，一个得到 index 的值
one really [INAUDIBLE] and one that sets it.
一个设置 index 的值
Okay, it's all about whether it's perceived as property.
好的，这取决于它是否被认定为一个属性
This index in effect is perceived by us as programmers
这个 index 实际上被我们程序员视为
it's a property right? It's, it's a property of the game
一个属性，对么？它是翻牌游戏的一个属性
is the index on the face of the card, so
它是唯一朝上的卡片的索引，所以
that's what you would do here. If another way of kind of
这就是这里使用计算属性的原因。另一种决定的方法
deciding is if the set or the get really does a lot of work.
是 set 或者 get 是否做了很多的工作
Like it's really crunching on something,
比如它处理了很多事情
you might wanna make that a function.
你可能想把它做成一个函数
Just so the people don't think, oh it's a lightweight
那样子的话，人们就不会认为，它是一个轻量
little property that I can get. Now, this might seem like
可以随时获取的属性。现在，它可能看起来
a lot of work but it's actually very very simple.
做了很多的工作，但是实际上非常非常简单
And then later in the lecture, probably on Wednesday,
之后可能在周三的课堂上
I'm gonna show you an even much simpler version of this.
我会展示给你们一个更简单的版本
When we learn a little bit more about Swift.
当我们学习更多一点 Swift 的内容后
But it really is not that much work it's just looking at
不过它真的不是那么多的工作，它只是查找
another data structure. But if you were doing a lot of work
另一个数据结构。但是如果你正在做很多的工作
then you probably want to do set and
那么你可能想要做 set 和 get（两个方法）
get to make it clear. But otherwise if it is
来让它清晰。否则的话如果概念上它是
a var if it seems like a var make it a var. Good question.
一个变量，感觉应该是个变量，就让它成为一个变量。非常好的问题
Alright where is my, here it is, keynote,
好的，我的 Keynote 在哪里，哦，在这
lets go back here, back to our slides. All right,
让我们返回这里，返回我们的幻灯片。好的
so the next thing we're gonna talk about is here,
我们要讨论的下一件事情
is another topic something we knew, access control. Okay, so
它是我们所了解的另一个主题，访问控制
what is access control? So, how many people have worked on
什么是访问控制？有多少人编写过一个项目
a project, an object oriented program project of more
一个有很多类的面向对象编程项目？
than a dozen classes? Okay, like two or
好的，像是两三个
three of you, four maybe, so, not very many of you. Okay,
同学，可能四个，总之并不是非常多
well when you're working on a very small project like that,
当你从事一个小项目的时候
you can call any method in any class, whatever,
你可以随意地在任何类里调用任何方法
you're probably the only programmer working on it.
你可能是工作的唯一的程序员
Or maybe you're working out with a buddy, and so
或者你和一个好朋友一起从事
you can talk to each other. Okay, but now imagine
所以你们可以互相交谈。但是想象
that you're working for Google. Or Facebook, or Apple,
你为 Google 工作，或者 Facebook 或者 Apple
or something like that, and this is kind of ridiculous.
等其他差不多的大公司，那这就有点荒唐了
But let's say you're working on concentration there. And
你正从事于翻牌游戏这个项目
there's a whole another group in another building that does
这里有另外一整个团队在另一幢建筑里从事
game design and they write the model. And
游戏设计，并且由它们编写模型
you are just the UI team for iOS,
你仅仅是 iOS 的 UI 团队
so you're only writing the view controller.
你只是写写视图控制器
Okay, well now, you don't wanna be calling each others
好的，那你不想只是混乱地互相调用代码
code just willy-nilly. Calling any old method like
你不会想调用任何老旧的方法
you wouldn't want your view controller cal someone like
比如你的视图控制器要调用
indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard.
indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
If those guys are like they got rid of that method
但如果某些人移除了那个方法
into the next month, and now your code broke. Now,
那么下一个月你的代码就不能用了
there are some methods that you have to be able to call
现在，这里有一些方法你一定能够去调用
over there and their code, and we're gonna make it clear
我们将会通过使用访问控制来表明
which ones of those are using access control.
哪些代码可以被我们调用
So access control is about having keyword that we're gonna put
所以访问控制是通过吧关键字放到
into our API, put it on the methods and vars,
放到 API，我们的方法和变量上
it says to other groups that we're programming with, yes,
告诉和我们合作的其他的小组说，是的
you are allowed to call this, I promise not to break this
你被允许调用这个，我保证不会让你的代码出问题
on you. It also tells them how to use your thing because
它也告诉他们如何使用你的东西，因为
the ones they're allowed to call or the ones they should
他们被允许调用的，也是他们应该使用的东西
be using to use your concentration game or
是为了使用你的翻牌游戏
whatever. So what are these keywords?
所以这些关键字是什么？
Well the first one is called internal. These are keywords
第一个叫做 internal（内部的）。这些关键字你都可以放到
you put in front of vars and funcs. Or even classes and
变量和函数前面，或者甚至是类和
structs, you can make entire classes and structs,
结构体前面，你可以对整个类和结构体
have their access controlled. So the default internal,
进行访问控制。所以默认的 internal
this one we never actually type in
实际上我们没来没敲过这个关键字
because it's the default. So all of the methods and
因为它是默认的。所以我们现在在翻牌游戏里完成的
vars that we've done so far in Concentration are all
所有方法和变量都是
internal. Now what does internal Access Control mean?
internal。internal 在访问控制中意味着什么呢？
It means anyone in your app, any object, any code anywhere
它意味着在你的应用中的任何人，任何对象，任何代码
can call that method or access that var. So it's pretty much
都可以调用这个方法或者访问这个变量。所以它在你的应用里是
unlimited control inside your app. Now as we start talking
非常不受限的一种控制。现在当我们谈论
about access control, we have to realise there's always two
访问控制的时候，我们不得不意识到这里总有两种
kinds of programming, there's writing an app,
编程类型，一种是编写应用
then there's writing a framework. Like Apple does,
一种是编写框架，像 Apple 做的
UI kit, okay? That's framework. A lot more access
UIKit，好么？那是框架。如果你在编写框架的时候
control issues if you're writing a framework. So
会有更多的访问控制事项
I'm gonna tell you what the things are for
所以我要告诉你对于编写一个框架来说
writing a framework but, We're not gonna really pay much
访问控制是什么，但是我们并不会花费太多
attention to them because we are only going to learn to
注意力到上面，因为我们这门课只学习
write apps in this course. So internal means everything in
编写应用。所以 internal 意味着你的应用
your app, or in your framework is, can access this code.
或者你的框架里的任何事物可以访问这块代码
So it's pretty much almost unlimited inside
所以它在你的框架里
your App's framework. Then there's the three privates.
是非常不受限制的。之后这里有三种私有的
These are very important, these are the ones you're
它们是非常重要的，它们是你会一直
gonna be using all the time. One is just private,
使用的。一个就叫 private
that means its internal implementation to this object,
它意味着是这个对象的内部实现
no other objects can call it. This is a good one to set,
没有其他的对象可以调用它，这是很好的访问控制
it keeps someone in the other group at Google and the other
它能避免在 Google 其他建筑里的小组
building from accessing that code. Because you're
访问那块代码。因为你让他
keeping it private, it's your private implementation.
成为私有的，这是你的私有实现
Private set is almost exactly the same, it's only for vars,
private(set) 大致上是一样的，它只针对变量
it means that setting this var is private, but getting it
它意味着赋值这个变量的权限是私有的，但是访问它
is not private. So you allow people to get the var, access
并不是私有的。所以你允许人们得到这个变量，访问
it, but they can not set it. That's you purview,
这个变量，但是不能给它赋值。那是你的权利
that's your internal implementation sets it.
你的内部实现可以给它赋值
We'll see a good example of that in concentration.
我们会在翻牌游戏里看到个好的例子
And then there's fileprivate. Fileprivate in a Swift file,
然后是 fileprivate，文件内私有。在一个 Swift 文件里
you can have multiple classes and structs in there,
你可以有多个类和结构体
you don't have to be just one class which is what we've done
不需要像我们现在这样一个文件只有一个类
so far and fileprivate means anything in that in that
而 fileprivate 的意思是，任何在那个
file can access each other, right. So classes,
文件里的都可以互相访问，也就是类
all classes in there, it can each others methods, okay,
所有的都可以访问 fileprivate 的方法（和变量）
that's what file private means. Okay, the other ones
这就是 fileprivate 的意思。好，其他的
are public and open, those are for framework writers.
public 和 open，这两个是给框架作者用的
Public means that people outside the framework
public 的意思是编写框架以外的人
can call it. Doesn't make sense for outside your app,
也可以调用它。在你的程序外使用是说不通的
that would never happen, so outside your framework.
这也不可能发生，所以是在框架外使用
And open means not only can people outside your framework
open 的意思是不仅框架外可以
call it but they could sub class that class,
调用，他们还可以继承那个类
override your methods all that stuff,
重写你的方法等
so open is like wide open, okay. We don't care about that
所以 open 是很开放的权限。但我们不用管
cuz we're only, we're not doing frameworks, right. So
因为我们只写程序，不会写框架，好吧，所以
we're gonna focus on private of the various privates.
我们主要关注这几种私有的访问权限
A good strategy to use these is pretty much put private on
最好的做法是基本都用 private
anything until you're sure, yeah I want someone else to be
除非你确信说，我想要其他人
able to call this method somewhere.
在其他地方能够调用这个方法
Right that's by default you should make things private. So
所以默认你应该让所有的都是 private
let's look a concentration, what it would look like to
所以让我们看看翻牌游戏，它看起来是什么样的
put access control on concentration and
如果我们给玩牌游戏加上访问权限的话
pay attention here because I'm gonna require in all your
你要注意了，因为我要求你所有的
homeworks going forward that you mark things properly.
之后的作业里正确地标记访问权限
I want you to mark things private if they should be
我想要你把私有的都标记为 private
private. Okay, cuz I wanna just make sure that you
因为我想要确保你
understand what this is all about. So let's go back here
理解了这是什么。那我们回到这里
to Xcode. Let's start with our ViewController.
到 Xcode 里，从 ViewController 开始
Okay, we have three classes, or three data structures,
好，我们有三个类，准确说是三个数据结构
our ViewController, Card, and Concentration. So let's start
我们的 ViewController、Card 和 Concentration。那我们
with ViewController. So this right here is our model. So
从 ViewController 开始改。这个是我们的模型
would we want our model to be public, to be not private?
我们想要模型是公开的，非私有的吗？
Well that depends, actually.
这不一定
It depends of what your model is and how it works. Often,
那取决于你的模型是什么，怎么工作的。一般来说
ViewControllers models are public by public I mean
ViewController 的模型是公开的。我这个公开不是指 public
non-private. We're inside an app so forget about public and
意思是非私有。我们写的是一个 App，所以你可以忽略 public 和
open keywords. I mean, when I say public I mean non-private.
open 这两个关键字。所以我所谓的 public 公开是指非私有
So a lot of times you do because you give a model to
而大部分时候都是这样的，因为你把一个模型提供给
a view controller and it displays it,
视图控制器，然后控制器就显示它
that's what it does. But that is not the case here. This one
这就是他的工作。但我们这里不是这样的情况。这里
wants to be private. And the reason it wants to be private
我们想要是 private 的。它应该是私有的
is because the number of pairs of cards in the game is
原因是 numberOfPairsOfCards
intimately tied to the UI, okay the number of
游戏里卡片的对数是和 UI 捆绑着的
cards we have in the UI. So if we wanted to make
是我们 UI 里卡的对数。如果我们想要
this public then we'd also have to make something public
让它公开的的话，我们也需要让另一个公开的
to specify the number of card buttons that we allow and
来指定我们允许的显示卡片的按钮的个数
we don't do that currently,
但我们现在并不是这样的
that's something that is in our little scene and
那现在是我们在 Interface Builder
interface builder, so we don't do it. So we keep this, we
的场景里设置的，所以我们不这样做。所以我们保持这个
keep this private. How about number of pairs of cards?
让他就是 private 的。那 numberOfPairsOfCards 呢？
Well, this is one where I don't mind if someone asks
嘛，这个我不介意如果其他人知道
what the number of pairs of cards is but
有多少对卡片，但是
setting the number of pairs of cards would be bad. But
设置有多少对卡片是不好的。但
the thing about this is it's already a get-only property.
这个的话，它已经是只读的属性了
You can't set it anyway, it derives it from other data.
你怎么都没法设置它，它是从其他数据衍生出来的
So we're just gonna make this private, sorry, not private.
所以我们就让他是 private 的。不好意思，让他不是 private
And we're gonna allow people to call this,
我们要让别人能够访问这个
people who are using my ViewController, they can say,
使用我这个 ViewController 人可以问
how many pairs of cards are there? But they can't set it,
这里有多少对卡片，但他们不能给它赋值
cuz this is not settable anyway. Okay, so
因为这个本来就没法赋值。好，所以
that's okay to make that in public.
这个是可以公开的
Same thing flipCount, I think flipCount,
flipCount 也是类似的，我认为 flipCount
it's okay for people to get it, but definitely, we don't
人们是可以读取它的，但肯定我们不
want people setting flipCount. That's something we do
想让人们赋值给 flipCount，那是我们
internally when the cards are flip, we implement flipCount.
在翻牌的时候内部实现的，我们管理的
So that's private for the setter, but will allow people
所以 setter 是 private 的，但我们允许其他人
to get the flipCount who are using our thing.
在使用的时候获得 flipCount
Our outlets, almost always we have private outlets.
我们这些 @IBOutlet，几乎我们都是保持 private
Cuz our private outlets,
因为我们私有的出口
these things, and even our actions these are all kind of
这些，甚至包括 @IBAction 操作，这些都是
internal implementation of how we implement our UI.
内部的 UI 实现
That's what a ViewController does it controls our UI.
这就是视图控制器的作用，控制 UI
Definitely something like update model from UI would be
肯定类似于 updateViewFromModel 的方法
private, that's internal implementation.
应该是 private 的，这也是内部实现
All this emoji business that's all private. Although you
这些表情相关的也应该是 private 的，虽然
could imagine trying to expose some public API eventually
你可以计划尝试最终暴露些公有 API
in this ViewController that let's someone who's using
让其他使用 ViewController 的人可以
our ViewController specify the emojis they want.
指定他们想用的表情
Like, you know, this theme required task that you have,
比如某个任务要求用某个主题
you could imagine that there was a way to specify I want
你可以设想我们有一种方法指定我想要
you mister view controller to play this game,
ViewController 玩这个游戏
but I want you to use this emoji as your theme.
但是我想要用这套表情作为主题
See, so you could imagine that something being public.
所以设想那种情况下可以是公开的
I don't think it would be exactly this API,
但我不认为会是和这个一样的 API
it would be some other kind of API,
那会是不同的 API
I'm not sure what they would let you set the emoji to
我不确定是什么样的，但它能让你设置使用的表情
use. We can't really make this public cuz we actually consume
这个我们是不能公开的，因为我们实际会消耗
this. This is a var and we consume it. We have obviously
这个数组；这是个变量，而我们会移除里面的内容。肯定
had to deal with that in your homework I'm sure. And
在你们的作业里要解决这个问题。还有
you know, this dictionary we're building on a fly,
你知道的，这个字典我们是及时构建的
we wouldn't want anyone messing with it, so
我们不会想其他人使用它，所以
I'm gonna keep all this private.
我让这些都是 private 的
This is an example of making it private first and
这就是个例子，先让这些都是 private
then I'm gonna think about what I want to be public.
之后我再考虑我要公开哪些
You see, the design approach there?
看到我们用的设计方法了吗？
All right, let's go look at card, so
好，我们再来看看 Card 结构体
here's Card. Card definitely, this has to be public.
这就是 Card。Card 里这个肯定是公开的
We need to know whether the cards are face up,
我们需要知道是否朝上
we, this has to be public. Unfortunately,
这个也必须是公开的。不幸的是
this has to be public. Cuz otherwise,
这个也得是公开的，因为否则的话
we can't tell if two cards are the same without that,
没有这个的话我们不能判断两张是否相同
but these two guys definitely don't need to be public.
但这两个肯定不用是公开的
This whole idea of I, making identierFactory that's purely
我这整个使用 identierFactory 只是为了
internal implementation, okay, so no reason for that to be
内部实现，所以没有理由把它
public. And this really, I'd love this to be private as
公开。然后这个 identifier，我虽然想要是 private
well, because a card it's either face up it's matched
因为这卡，我就想知道是否朝上，是否配对了
whether it's the same as another card,
而两张卡是否相同
I shouldn't have to look an identifier to find that.
我不应该靠 identier 标识符来判断
I should be able to say the this card == the other card,
我应该能用 一张卡 == 另一张卡 来判断
wouldn't that be cool? And yeah it is cool and
那不更好么？是的，那是挺酷的
we're gonna be doing that, in, later in this lecture or next
而我们也就会这样做，要么等会儿这节课，要么
lecture. Um, this is really kind of gross but for now we
下节课。我挺讨厌这个，但现在我们
have to leave that public because otherwise we do,
就让他保持公开，因为否则的话
we can't tell what two cards are the same. Okay,
我们就不能判断两张卡是否相同了吧
here's the Concentration game, this is a really interesting
然后这个是 Concentration 游戏本身，这是个很有趣的
case of private and public because, here is an object,
决定私有还是公开的例子，因为这个对象
a model that is intended to be used by some UI somewhere,
模型本身就是给其他的某个 UI 使用的
okay. It's very intentional use kind of thing, and
就是为了被使用而存在的
there's some things we know are private,
这里有我们知道是 private 的
like this guy for sure, indexOfTheOneAndOnlyFaceUpC-
比如肯定有这里的 indexOfOneAndOnlyFaceUpCard
ard, we don't need someone using us to know that,
我们不需要让使用的人知道
they don't need to know that.
他们不需要知道这个
And in fact, if we left that public, someone using us would
实际上，如果我们把它公开的话，使用我们的人会
be like when am I supposed to set that, I wonder?
想，“我要把它设置为什么呢？”
Okay, but it has nothing to do with it, it's internal to our
但他们和这个是无关的，这是我们内部
implementation. Cards has to be public
实现用的。cards 必须要是公开的
because otherwise the UI can't display the cards.
否则的话 UI 就不能显示卡片了
However, cards being flipped up and down or
但是把牌翻面，或是
matching that's my job. So I am gonna make this one private
让他们配对,这是我的工作，所以我要让它是 private(set)
set, okay, so this is gonna be yeah you can look at my cards
所以这个会是，使用的人可以看我有哪些牌
if you wanna use Concentration game but I am responsible for
如果他们在用 Concentration 游戏的话。但我负责
setting face up and is matched. So
把卡片翻面，设置是否配对了，所以
you can see this one's clearly private set,
我们可以明确地看出这个是 private(set)
everyone see that? Yeah. >> So for that you can access
大家都看到了吗？>> 所以 private(set) 就是你可以获得
the cards but you can't access the methods or
cards 数组的元素，但是你不能访问元素的方法
properties associated with it? >> Yeah, so
或者实例的属性吗？>> 好，所以
the question is when it's like this does that mean I
问题是用 private(set) 是否意味着
can access the cards but I can't access the methods that
我可以访问 cards 的元素，但是不能访问方法
are on the cards you mean? No the methods on the cards,
这是你的问题吧？不，Card 实例的方法
that's over here, those are public, okay,
那是在这里定义的，这些是公开的
those are not internal so I can access those from here,
这些不是内部实现，所以我这里可以访问他们
okay? But you remember that this is a value type, so
但你要记得 Card 是值类型，所以
I can't set is face up and stuff, I can only set that
我不能赋值给 isFaceUp 这些，我只能直接
directly in the array. Like I'm doing right here. You see,
通过数组给它赋值，就像我这里这样，你看
here I'm modifying the thing in place in the array.
我这里直接更改了在数组里的 Card 实例的属性
That's the only way to do it. Well, I can't do this if this
这是我唯一能用的方法。而在其他地方是不能这样做的，如果这个
is private set. Okay? Cuz this is a value type.
是 private(set) 的话，对吧？因为这个是值类型
So this makes it so this, this it's kind of like it's a let.
这个让它有点像是 let 声明的常量
This almost makes it like a let for
对于其他人
other people, people other than me. And then, and so
private(set) 就像是 let 一样，也就是
you can't touch anything in an array when it's a let. So
在数组是 let 常量的时候你不能修改数组的元素
that's a really cool feature of value types.
所以这是值类型很酷的特性
And remember that array's a value type and
然后，要记得数组是值类型
card is a value type. So that whole thing is frozen for
Card 也是值类型，所以这整个就被“冻”住了
people who, you can't be modified for outside people.
其他人就没法修改它
But for us, it's private set so
但 private(set) 对于我们来说
we can do anything we want in there which we have been
我们可以像现在这样为所欲为
doing. All right. And then of course, choose card.
好吧。然后肯定的，chooseCard
That's our fundamental public API. So we got to leave that
这是我们基础的公有 API，所以我们就让他
not private, okay. That's how people do it. And
不是私有的，这是别人调用的方法。然后
initializing, initializers can be made private as well. But
构造过程，构造器也可以是私有的，但是
this one obviously can't be private because otherwise no
这个不能是私有的，否则的话
one could create a game, all right. So that's it. Everyone
没有人可以新建一个游戏，好，就是这样
got that? Now, while I'm here, I'm gonna show you another
大家都明白吧？现在我在这里还要给你展示另一种
API protection thing that's different from access control.
方法来保护 API。不是靠访问权限控制
That's still good, which is using assertions, okay.
这也是中好方法，那就是使用 assert，断言
Do anyone know what an assertion is from other
大家从其他语言知道了 assert/断言是什么吗？
languages? An assertion is just a function that you call
断言就是一个你调用的 assert 函数
where you assert something to be true. And if it's not,
以此来确保某个条件是成立的；如果不是的话
your program crashes and print out an error.
你的程序就会崩溃，然后打印出错误信息
And you put it in your code, the asserts are ignored when
你这代码里使用 assert 函数，但发布到
you ship to the App Store. But when you're in development,
App Store 时会被忽略。但你在开发的时候
it'll be crashing your program, which is good,
他会让你的程序崩溃，这是好事情
cuz it takes the debugger right to the assertion failed.
因为调试器会带你到断言失败了的地方
And asserts are a great way to protect your API. For example,
断言是保护你 API 的好方法，比如说
look at this API, chooseCard.
看 chooseCard 这个 API
What if someone says at index -1?
如果别人传的 index 是 -1 呢？
Or at index 100 and they're only 12 cards.
或者我们只有 12 张，但他们选择在索引 100 的卡
Okay, that's gonna crash somewhere deep inside here,
那种情况程序会在这里的某个地方崩溃
probably like maybe here or
可能是在这里或者
something like that. And if I'm the Google guys again, and
类似的地方。再次设想如果我是 Google 的员工
these guys are in another building and
他们在另一栋建筑里
I accidentally pass -1 here and I don't know what's. And
我不小心传了 -1 给 index，然后
the crash happens in here, I'm gonna need to have this code,
程序在这里面崩溃了，那我需要拿到这份代码
and look in there, and I'm debugging it.
然后到这里面找，去调试它
That code belongs to someone in another building,
这段代码是在别的地方的其他人写的
why would I ever wanna be in here debugging it? Instead,
为什么我会想去帮他调试代码？取而代之
the guys in the other building should put an assert here.
在另一个建筑里的人应该在这里使用断言
That asserts that the cards indices contain that index.
assert(cards.indices.contains(index), )
Okay, if the card's indices don't contain this index,
如果 cards 数组的索引 indices 不包含 index
then we're going to crash, if we're in development and so,
如果我们在开发的过程中，那程序就会崩溃
then we want to put some kind of crash message here.
然后这里我们应该放崩溃的时候显示的信息
I like to put the name of the struct or class and
我个人喜欢放这个结构体或类的名字
the function which chooseCard. I even like to include
以及函数名，也就是 chooseCard。我甚至喜欢包括
the actual arguments that you passed so you can see what you
传给我的实际参数，这样调用的人就能知道
passed there and then, I give the message. In this case,
传给我的参数。最后是我的错误信息，这里
something like chosen index not in the cards.
就用比如“选择的索引不在 cards 数组里”
So that, so now if someone calls to choose
这样的话，其他人调用 chooseCard
card at minus one, it's gonna crash right away and
传入负一，那就会直接崩溃
put that on the console. And they're gonna be like,
然后显示这个信息到控制台里。调用的人就知道
oh, shows the index not on the card, oh, and
哦，说索引不在 cards 数组里，哦
I passed minus one. You see, they're gonna one stop shop.
我传的是 -1。你看，一步到位
Know what they did. And with the similar thing thing down
能知道他们干了什么。下面这也是类似的
here for number of pairs of cards because it's illegal to
对于 numberOfPairsOfCards，是不能有
have 0 or less pairs of cards. You have to have at least one
0 或者更少对卡片的。你必须要有至少一对
pair of card. So here I'm just gonna have the assertion be
卡片，所以我这里就加个断言
that the number of Pairs Of Cards is greater than 0.
确保 numberOfPairsOfCards 大于 0
And if there is an error then I'm gonna say yes,
如果不是的话，那我就会说
I'm in the concentrations Init and
我在 Concentration.init 里
you passed me this number of pairs of cards right here and
然后是你传给我的这个 numberOfPairsOfCards
the problem here is that you must have at least
问题是你必须至少有
one pair of cards. Okay? So, you see how I'm, I'm using
一对卡片。好吧？你看到我是怎么使用
assert here to kinda protect my API against improper use.
断言来保护我的 API 不被错误地使用
Question back there? Yeah? >> Sorry when you,
后面同学有什么问题？>> [学生提问]
Sorry when you- >> When would you set init
>> 能重复你的问题么？>> 你什么时候会让 init
as private? >> Oh, so
是 private 的呢？>> 哦
the question is when would I set my init as private, okay.
这个同学问我什么时候会有私有的构造器
Well, you might have a complicated object that
举个例子，你可能会有一个复杂的对象
only creates instances of itself. For example,
只允许它自己构造实例，通过比如
with static methods or something like that.
static 的静态方法一类的来实现
Or you might have multiple inits. Some of which you'll allow
或者你有多个 init。有些你允许
other people to call. But some of which you call internally
其他人调用，而有些只是你内部使用的
to create, okay. You might even have public ones that is
你甚至可能有公开的构造器
part of their implementation called the private ones. Okay,
会调用私有的构造器来实现
cuz inits can call each other which we'll talk about on
因为构造器可以调用另一个构造器。这个我们会在
Wednesday. So that's why you might have some private. Okay,
星期三讲。这就是为什么可能你的某些构造器是私有的
everybody cool with access control and
大家都对访问权限和断言没问题了吧？
assertions? All right, back to the slides.
好，我们接着讲幻灯片
Where are we? Here, okay. Cool one, all right extensions. So
我们讲到哪里了来着？这里，这个很厉害，extension
extensions are super powerful. They're kind of like
扩展非常强大，它就像一种武器
a weapon you'll want to be careful when you're wielding,
当你使用的时候需要额外小心
because you can go crazy with them. And what an extension
因为你可能会走火入魔。在 extension 里
allows you to do is add vars and functions to other classes
你可以给其他的类添加变量和方法
even if you don't have the code to those classes.
即使你没有那个类的源代码也能做到
Even if there in another frame work like UI Kits or something
即使那个类属于另一个如 UIKit 一类的框架
like that. So you can add vars and methods to Int, you can add
你可以给 Int 添加变量和方法，你可以添加
it to UI Button. You can add it UI View Controller.
到 UIButton 里，可以添加给 UIViewController
Anything you want. Okay? So this is a very, very, very
任何你想要的类，知道了吧？所以这是个非常非常
powerful feature. And really I'm sure what's swimming in your mind about
非常强大的功能。我确信能猜到你们脑袋里想的
the possibilities is nothing compared to the actual
各种可能性只是实际能实现的微不足道
possibilities because there are other data structures that
的一部分，因为还有很多数据结构
we haven't even talked about that adding an extension to
我们还没有讲到，但给它们添加扩展
really is powerful and we'll get to that by end of
是真的很实用，我们会在星期三
Wednesday as well. The basic line of it is, is very simple.
下课之前讲。要添加扩展很简单
You just use the keyword extension and the name of
你只需要用关键字 extension，然后数据类型的名字
the struct or class you wanna add a var property to and
就是你想要添加变量的结构体或类的名字
then just put the thing you want in there.
然后在大括号里写你要扩展的内容
Now, it has one very some serious restriction which is
但是有一个限制是
that it can have no storage. This extension, this code that
扩展没有存储空间。作为扩展，这些代码
you're extending this other thing, it can have no vars
扩展了另一个数据类型，它是不能扩展
that are storage. It could have vars that are computed.
存储属性的。但它可以添加计算属性
But it can't have any vars with storage. So
但任何存储属性都不行
that does restrict the kind of thing that you can
这肯定会限制你们想添加的
add to a function. Okay, but you kinda turn out that
某些功能。但其实
restriction is actually a good restriction. It's not like
这个限制是很正确的，并不是说
the too bad they could invent it with storage. You
它们水平太差实现不了。你
actually don't want storage, and you will see as we
其实并不会想要有存储，而且你会从我们
go along why that is. So, this feature as you might imagine
之后讲的领悟到为什么。正如你所想的，这个功能
is easily abused and the number one ways to get abuse,
经常被滥用，而其中最常见的情况是
and I encourage you not to abuse at this way is you do
我建议你也不要这样做，那就是
not want to add a var or a func to class that doesn't
你不应该添加一个变量或方法到某个类
make sense for that class. It's a real temptation for
但对于那个类来说是毫不相关的。最吸引人的
example for an Int or String to add a function that has to
是比如扩展 Int 或 String，添加一个
do with concentration. Some concentration specific method
只为了翻牌游戏而存在的方法
you're adding to string cuz it'll clean up your code or
好让你的代码更简洁或者
look nice or whatever But you really don't wanna do that.
看起来更好看，但是你不应该这样做
The only method and functions you wanna add to string or
你想给 String 添加的方法和变量
methods that make string a better class. They make it a better
应该是为了让 String 成为一个更好的字符串
string not they make it knows about concentration. Now,
而不是为了让它了解翻牌游戏
it's probably possible to add string methods to make it
虽然可以添加方法给字符串来让它
know about concentrations that nothing really wrong with it.
了解翻牌游戏，这也不是什么错误的做法
It's just kind of bad design. Okay so
但并不是很好的设计。所以
this extension's feature like I said is very powerful,
就像我说的扩展是很强大的功能
since you're just beginning here, you can think of it at
但你们才刚开始学，你目前可以把它当作
the beginning as just a way to add utility, functions and
只是一种方法来添加实用工具，方法
things like that to clean up your code.
和其他东西来整理你的代码
Okay, that the first level of learning about extensions so
这就是我们对 extension 的简单认识
I am going to show you how we could do that for
我会给你们展示我们如何扩展
example in Concentration. So let's go to concentration and
比如我们的翻牌游戏，那我们回到翻牌游戏
use an extension to add something interesting and
使用扩展来添加有趣的东西
what interesting thing we are going to do is we are going to
我们要做的有趣的事情是
go to our view controller over here and
到 ViewController 里
look at this code right here which is kind of messy.
然后看看这有些乱的代码
Right here. Okay? What is messy about this code?
就这个。为什么说它很乱呢？
Well. Okay. All I really wanna do is remove a random emoji.
因为我想要做的只是随机移除一个表情
And you have to have a whole other line of code.
但却为此多写了一行代码
And that line of code has this horrendous amount of. Changing
而且这行代码还很复杂，转换
from unsigned ints to regular ints and all that stuff.
无符号整数和整数这些乱七八糟的
So it just really looks bad, and it's hard to read,
看起来很不好看，而且很难读
it's hard to understand what is going in here.
而且很难理解到底发生了什么
I'm having to do so many type conversions, stuff like that.
我需要太多的类型转换等
It's awful, okay? Really what I'd like to do is generate
非常糟糕是吧？我想要的只是生成
a random number and put it right here. So what if int,
一个随机数然后放到这里。如果整数
the type int, had a var which gave me a random
Int 类型有个变量可以给我随机的某个
integer? Okay, that's a very int thing, nothing to
整数该多好？这确实和整数相关
do with concentration, it's just int thing.
和翻牌游戏无关，只是整数的功能
It gives me a random integer. So we're going to extend int
它就给我一个随机的整数，所以我们要扩展 Int
to give back a random integer. Specifically, we're gonna make
来随机返回某个整数。更具体实现是
it so that when you ask an int please give me a random
我们要去请某个整数返回这个随机整数
integer it gives a random integer between 0 and that
那个随机数会在零到它本身之间
int. Okay, so if I say five, I can even say, I'm gonna be
比如我用 5，我还能够用
able to say here let x equal five dot random integer.
let x = 5.随机整数
And I'm gonna call this thing arc4random, this var.
我把这个随机整数变量叫 arc4random
Because I'm gonna use arc4random to generate it and
因为我是用 arc4random 生成它的
people know the semantics of arc4random which is
而且大家都知道 arc4random
a random a number
就是随机数
between 0 and another number. So this is, I'm gonna make
0 到另一个数之间的随机数。我会让
it so this will work and that will give me 0, 1, 2, 3, or 4.
这段代码通过编译，而且返回 0, 1, 2, 3, 4 中的一个
So how do I do that? Extension int and then in here
那我要怎么做呢？ extension Int 然后
I put this var arc4random. I have to say what type it is,
把 var arc4random 放在里面。我必须要声名它的类型
it's also gonna be an int. It could could be a string or
它也是 Int 类型的。扩展里的变量也可以是 String
whatever but it's also gonna be an int. And
或是其他的类型，但这个是 Int 类型的
I'm essentially gonna return all this mess right here. So
它最终返回的就是所有这里这些乱七八糟的
I'm just gonna cut that out of there. I'm gonna return this.
我就把它剪切然后粘贴到 return 后面
But it's not a random number between 0 and
但这里就不是 0..<emojiChoices.count
emojiChoices.count, it's a random order between 0 and
之间的随机数了，应该是 0 到
what? Yes, whoa, I wish I could give extra credit or
是什么？没错，我希望我能够给附加分或者
like Mehran, throwing some candy out there or
像 Mehran（斯坦福 CS106A 的教授）一样扔糖给你
something because yes absolutely, it's between 0 and
因为没错，它应该是 0 到
self. Because this is a var in int. And so self is the int
self 之间。因为这是 Int 到属性，所以 self 就是
you sent it to. Which is really kind of cool. So now,
你访问这个属性的整数。这还蛮有趣的
since int can do this, all we need to do right here is we
现在 Int 有了这个属性，我们这里需要做的就是
don't need any of this junk up here. Instead of randomIndex,
我们可以不要这些乱七八糟的 randomIndex
we're just gonna say emojiChoices.count.arc4random.
我们只用写 emojiChoices.count.arc4random
Okay, so, that cleaned up our code a lot. Now,
这样我们就让代码整洁了许多
if we were to do something like this, and we wanted to
如果我们写了这段代码，而我们想要
be really good programmers, we'd look at this and say, hm,
做优秀的程序员，我们看了这个应该想
what if self is 0? Eh, this is not gonna work,
如果 self 是 0 怎么办？这个就不行了
cuz arc4random_uniform doesn't work, but
因为 arc4random_uniform 不接受 0。那
what if self is negative? Actually, if self were
如果 self 是负数怎么办？事实上如果 self
negative, maybe I could do a random number between 0 and
是负数的话，我应该可以随机选择 0 到
that negative number. So, I might decide, I'm gonna say if
那个那个负数之间的整数。所以我决定判断
self is greater than 0, then I'll do this.
如果 self 大于 0，我们就用这段代码
Else if self is less than 0, then I'm gonna almost do this.
否则如果 self 小于 0，那代码基本不变
What I'm gonna do, is I'm gonna say return minus this,
我要做的就是返回负的这个
the absolute value of myself. Okay,
上限用 abs 取 self 的绝对值
abs is just a global function. But I could also just say
这个 abs 就是个全局函数，但我也可以用
minus self cuz I checked to see if it's negative.
-self 因为我已经知道它是负数了
Or else if self is 0, which would be the else case here,
否则如果是 0，也就是 else 分支
then maybe I'll just return 0. So if you say, 0,
就可以直接返回 0。如果你用 0.arc4random
give me a random number, it gives you a 0. So here I've
来获取一个随机数，它就会返回 0。这样我
made it that this never crashes. This doesn't have to
就保证它绝对不会让程序崩溃了，这个也不必要是
be an optional int and it gives a reasonable response.
可选的整数，同时返回的也是合理的结果
See, and that's pretty good. When you add vars and
看，这挺不错的。当你添加变量
functions to any class, not even just extensions,
或者函数到任何类型的时候，不只是在扩展里
you want them to have good semantics, sensible semantics.
你应该让他们有好的，合理的语义
And you don't generally don't want them to crash which is
而且一般你也不希望它容易让程序崩溃
what this would have done otherwise.
也就是我们之前一行代码的实现
If you sent it to -3.
比如你通过 -3 访问的话
Everyone see how this makes our code a lot more readable.
大家看到扩展让我们的程序更加易读了吗？
And how we added something that was sensible for int.
以及我们是如何给 Int 添加了合理的功能？
All right, that's it, let's get back to our slides again.
好，这就是扩展，让我们继续讲幻灯片
Here is arc4random. Okay, optionals,
这是我们刚讲的 arc4random，接着讲可选类型
the dreaded word optionals. So I told you last
听起来很吓人的 Optional。我上周
week that an optional is just a regular old type in Swift.
说 Optional 在 Swift 里就是个普通的类型
In fact it's a enum,
事实上它是个 enum
an enumeration. So let's learn about enum because enum is
枚举类型。我们先来学习下 enum，因为
another thing I wasn't able to work it into concentration,
另一个我没法加到翻牌游戏的就是枚举
although I am gonna work it into next week's demo. Okay,
虽然我下周的演示里会用到
our drawing demo. But I want to explain what it is so
我们演示绘画的程序。但我想先解释它是什么
that I can explain what optionals are a little better.
这样我就能更好地把可选类型解释清楚
So an enum is just like an enum in other languages.
enum 和其他语言的枚举类型是一样的
It's a data type, just like struct is a type or
就是种数据类型，就像 struct 是一种类型
class is a type, enum is a type.
class 也是种类型一样，enum 也是种类型
Exactly the same, you can use it in exactly the same places.
都是数据类型，可以在同样的地方使用
It's just that it has only discrete values. Here's
只不过区别就是枚举类型包含了所有不同的可能性
a FastFoodMenuItem enum, it can only be hamburger, fries,
枚举 FastFoodMenuItem，快餐店的菜单上只会有汉堡，薯条
drink, or cookie. That's it, it can't be anything else
饮料或是饼干，就这些，不能是其他任何的东西
besides one of those four things, so
只能是这四种中的一种
that's what an enum is. Enums are value types, like structs,
这就是枚举。枚举也是值类型，和结构体一样
they get copied as you pass them around. Now enums in
当你把它四处传递的时候会被拷贝
Swift little bit more powerful then your typical enum because
在 Swift 里的枚举比其他语言的枚举更厉害
each case can also have what's called associated data, or
因为每个 case 还能有与之关联的数据
an associated value. So in my fast food item one my
叫作关联值。比如我 FastFoodMenuItem 里的
hamburgers have the number of patties,
hamburger 的关联值就是 numberOfPatties
is it a double burger or a triple or
汉堡的肉饼是双层的还是三层的还是
a single? The fries has the size of the fries,
只有一层？fries 的关联值是薯条的大小
a large fry, or a small. And I've even used another enum,
大号还是小号。这里我用了另一个枚举
you see down here at the bottom.
就是下面你看到的这个
I have another, oops, my thing work here. There it is.
我有另一个，让我把它鼠标聚焦在这里
This is not very good. Okay, we got it. There it is. So
这个并不是很容易操作。好，终于，就这个
I can use another enum there to do the size of it and
所以我可以用另一个枚举表示它的大小
then drink. It has two pieces of associated data.
然后 drink 的关联值是两个数据构成的
Okay, let's see if we can get this working for that.
让我来试试能不能好好聚焦
And if you look at its two pieces of associated data,
你看这关联值的两部分
look at the first one.
这第一个
That string, it has no name. These other ones have names,
那个 String 没有名字，其他的都有
like number of patties, size, this one has no name for
像 numberOfPatties 和 size，但饮料的第一个
the first one, it does have a name for the second one.
没有名字，虽然它第二个是有名字的
First the strings and then an int. Now the names here don't
一个是 String，一个是 Int。但这个名字并
matter that much because when we extract this information,
不是那么重要，因为当我们提取这个信息的时候
we're gonna be able to give it our own name anyway,
我们总是要给它另取一个名字的
kind of like tuples. In fact, these look a lot like tuples,
就像元组一样。关联值其实和元组很像
don't they? These little associated datas,
不是吗？这些关联值
they're kind of like tuples because you can have as many
它们挺像元组的，因为你可以有任意数量
of them as you want, you specify the type,
的数据，你指定它们的类型
they have names, they're super simple, and
它们可以有名字，非常简单
they look very much like tuples. So, anyway,
看起来和元组很像。所以
so this is what it looks like to declare an enum with
这就是声明带有关联值的枚举
associated data. Now, how do you assign an enum?
的方法。那你怎么赋值一个枚举呢？
So here is two variables, one called menu item,
这里有两个变量，一个是 menuItem
one called other item. They are of type FastFoodMenuItem,
另一个叫 otherItem，都是 FastFoodMenuItem
that's their type. And so I set them just by saying
这是它们的类型。然后我给它们赋值就用
FastFoodMenuItem dot the case I want.
FastFoodMenuItem.我想要的 case
And if it has associated data, I have to provide it.
如果那种情况有关联值，那我也需要相应地提供
So the only time you can set the associated data of an enum
唯一我能指定枚举的关联值的时候
is when you assign it. That's the only time. Okay,
就是在赋值的时候，这是唯一一次机会
you can't go back later and change this to be a triple,
你不能之后又回来然后把双层汉堡改成三层的
because this is fundamentally a double burger.
因为它已经就是个双层汉堡了
That's what it is. And it's never, if it changed, it would
它就是它，不会再变了。如果关联值发生了改变
change into a completely different thing. All right, so
它就会变成一个完全不同的东西。好
you don't change the patties, got that? All right, so, when
所以你不能更改关联值，知道了吗？好
you're setting these values by the way of course you can use
当你在设置这些值的时候，当然你可以用
type inference, but only on one side of that equals. So
类型推导，但只能在等号的某一侧使用
you could say menuItem equals FastFoodMenuItem.hamburger.
你可以说 menuItem = FastFoodMenuItem.hamburger
Which was what was on the previous slide, or
也就是和之前那页一样的写法，或者
you could say otherItem of type FastFoodMenuItem equals
说 FastFoodMenuItem 类型的 otherItem
.cookie. You see,
是 .cookie。看
I've just basically moved the type to the other side. But
我基本上就是把类型移到了另一边
you can't say yet another item equals .cookie. Swift doesn't
但你不能说 otherItem = .cookie，因为 Swift 没有
know enough there to infer the type on the other side. There
得到足够的信息来推导等号右边是什么类型的
could be other enums with .cookie in it, for example,
可能有其他的枚举也有 .cookie，比如
that you might add later. And then all of a sudden your code
你可能之后会添加这么一个，那么立刻你的代码
won't compile because it doesn't know. So
就肯定编译不了了，因为 Swift 不知道选哪个
it just says from the start, I don't know what that is.
所以 Swift 决定从一开始就说不知道是什么类型
Now how do you check what an enum is?
那你要如何判断枚举是哪种情况呢？
You do not use equals. So you don't say,
你不用 == 判断，你不用写
if this menu item equals a hamburger then whatever, okay,
if menuItem == .hamburger 那就怎样怎样
you do not use equals, you use switch. Again, other languages
你不用 == 判断，应该用 switch。同样的，其他语言
have switch. Switch is more powerful in Swift.
也有 switch，但 Swift 里的 switch 更强大
This is the basic use of switch right here, where I'm
这里的只是 switch 的基本用法，我只是
just looking at every possible case that it could be, and
逐一判断了所有可能的情况
if it's that case, I do a little bit of code.
如果是这种情况，那我就运行这段代码
So here I'm just printing out what the various cases are so
这里我只是打印出了是什么情况
if it's hamburgers, for example,
比如如果是汉堡的话
you can see that I'm printing burger.
你看到我打印的就是汉堡的英文
Notice that I'm ignoring the associated data here which is
注意我这里忽略了关联值，这是
perfectly fine.
完全没问题的
You're allowed to completely ignore the associated data
你可以完全忽略关联值
when you're checking the state with switch. Now
当你用 switch 语句判断的时候是可以的
switch requires you to address every single case. You are not
注意 switch 语句要求你穷举所有的情况，你不能
allowed to look at only two of the cases. But, of course,
只是判断其中的两种，但当然
it's got something that can help you with that. Oh yes,
Swift 提供了帮你解决这个问题的方法
by the way, you see I've taken away the FastFoodMenuItem
顺便一提，你看到我把 FastFoodMenuItem 省略了
in front of hamburger, fries, drink, and coke. Becuase swift
只剩下 .hamburger, .fries, .drink 和 .coke
can infer that, you're switching on a menu item, so
因为这个 Swift 是可以推导的，你 switch 的是 menuItem
it knows this is a FastFoodMenuItem, so
Swift 知道那是个 FastFoodMenuItem，所以
you can take those away. All right, so if you have one of
你可以省略这个。好，如果你这里有个
the cases, and you don't wanna do anything, you can just
case 决定什么也不做，那你可以
break. Break means break out of this switch. So
用 break，也就是跳出 switch
that's a way to do nothing in this case. So, right here,
这就是什么也不做的方法。这里的这个
this code, we print nothing because the hamburger case,
这段代码不会打印任何内容，因为在是 .hamburger 时
the menu item is a hamburger with two patties, and
menuItem 是双层的汉堡
that hamburger case does nothing, so
是汉堡情况下的代码什么也不做
we'll just break out and do nothing. Similarly,
我们直接 break 跳出 switch。类似的
if you want to do something for all the rest of the cases,
如果你希望让剩余的情况都做某件事情
like here I only want to do something for
比如我只想要在是汉堡或是薯条的情况下
hamburger and fries. Actually I do nothing for hamburger and
做某些事情，更准确的说是汉堡我什么也不做
I do something for fries.
是薯条我做另外的事情
In all other cases, I just want to print other, then you
其他所有的情况我都打印说是其他
can use default instead of case whatever. Now in switch,
那你就可以用 default 来代替其他的情况。switch
you can switch any type, you can even switch on a string.
可以用来判断任何类型，你甚至可以 switch 字符串
But if you switch on a string, you'd have to have case A,
但如果你要判断 String 的话，你需要判断 case "A":
case B, case C, case AA, case AB, you see what I mean?
case "B", "C", "AA", "AB": 等等。知道我什么意思了吗？
You'd have to have every case in the world.
你需要列举所有可能存在的字符串
So of course you're going to use default in a string case
所以肯定你需要在 switch 字符串的时候用 default
switch case the couple
你 switch 里列举一些
ones you wanna case, then you would default the rest. So
你想要的情况，然后其他的就用 default 处理
default is a must. Even for enums we use it quite a bit,
所以字符串必须用 default。有的时候枚举我们也会用到
all right? So that's break an enum. So
听懂了吧？这就是 break 和枚举
if this were a cookie then it would print other. All right,
这里如果是 .cookie 的话，那就会打印 other
multiple lines, I just wanted to make clear that, multiple
接着是多行代码。我只是想澄清
lines of code are allowed, it doesn't have to be one line.
每个 case 里是可以有多行代码的，不一定只有一行
That was just cuz I'm on slides here,
之前只有一行是因为我在讲幻灯片
I'm trying to make everything fit, and
我希望能装下所有的内容
there's no fall through. So in this case, I've got fries,
还有，每个 case 并不会贯穿到下一个，比如这里
you see up there at the top, fries,
你看上面的 .fries
large fries there. And
它是 .large，大号的薯条
so this code would print out yummy fires and that's it. So
所以这段代码会打印 yummy fries，然后就完了
I have multiple lines of code in there under fries,
我 .fries 的 case 里有多行代码
two lines of code, and it does not fall through and do drink,
两行代码，而且它也不会贯穿到 .drink 里去
like in other languages. In C, things fall through, in switch
像 C 这些其他语言就会贯穿到 .drink
but they don't fall through here. There is a keyword
Swift 里并不会。但有一个关键字
called fallthrough that would let you fall through, but
叫 fallthrough 可以让你贯穿到下一个 case
by default it doesn't. By the way, the same way that it inferred
但默认是不会的。顺便一提，就像推导
the type all along in here, it can for that type as well.
switch 里每个 case 的类型一样，Swift 也推到了它的类型
I don't have to say size,fries size enum.large,
我并不需要用 size: FryOrderSize.large
I can just say, .large because it knows that the associated
我可以直接用 .large，因为 Swift 知道薯条的
data of fries is s fries size enum. Okay,
关联值是 FryOrderSize 这个枚举
now, what if I want to get the associated data. So I do,
那如果我现在想要得到关联值怎么办呢？
I am interested in it. We do that with switch as well,
我很感兴趣。这个我们也可以用 switch
we just do this little let business. See the little lets.
我们只需要加上些 let，看到这里的 let 了吗？
In all the cases that you want this associated data,
对于所有你想要关联值的 case
you don't have to do it in all cases, but
你并不需要每个 case 都这样做
in the ones you want it? You just say, open parentheses,
但对于你想要的，你在括号里面就用
let and a name of a little local variable for
let 和你给关联值取得作为本地变量的名字
each of the associated pieces of data. Now,
对于每个关联值都这样做
that little name that you use, so if this were a coke see it
现在你就可以使用那个名字了。比如这里是可乐的话
would print whatever ounces coke right there, cuz just
那就会打印出有多少盎司的可乐。因为它把
getting the Coke into brand. It's getting the ounces into
brand 赋值为 "Coke"，把 ounces 赋值为
something called ounces, and then it's doing that print.
有多少升，然后执行那条 print 语句
This naming does not have to be the same names
这里的不一定非要用同样的命名
as you declared the enum from. In fact,
可以和枚举定义时不一样。事实上
if we look at this Coke one right here, this let brand,
如果我们看到刚才的可乐，这里用 let brand
remember in the original enum that didn't even have a name,
但我们原本的枚举是甚至是没有给它名字的
it was just a string, right? And it had ounces,
只说了它是 String 类型，好吧？但 ounces 是有的
colon ounces, and up here with hamburger, pattyCount,
ounces: Int。上面 hamburger 的 pattyCount
that was called patties in the original declaration. So
那个本来的定义里叫 numberOfPatties
again, does this not look familiar to tuples, right?
你们不觉得这个和元组很像吗？
You can rename them when you're getting the information
当你从其中获取数据的时候可以重命名
out of them. So this is how you extract data
所以这就是你怎么获得
out of the associated types. Very simple, and
关联值里的数据，非常简单
again it's optional you don't have to have it there.
再次说一下这个不是必须的，你不一定非要有关联值
Also enums, they're like structs and classes.
然后枚举与类和结构体一样
They can have methods and they can have vars, but no storage.
它们可以有方法，也可以有变量，但是没有存储空间
All the storage of an enum is in which case it is and
枚举的存储空间是只包含属于哪个 case
that case's associated data.
和那个 case 的关联值
That's it, you can't have many other vars or anything else.
就这些，你不能有其他的变量
So the only vars you could have are computed vars.
所以你能有的变量都是计算变量
So see the example I have here where it's calories,
比如你看我这里的例子，卡路里
where you'd compute the calories of that menu item
你会计算那个菜单项的卡路里
that would have to be a computed type. Can't store
那必须要是计算属性。枚举不能
anything in an enum except for the associated data right
存储任何内容，唯一的是可以有像这里的关联值
there. Now if you're writing a func like this one,
如果你在写一个像这样的方法
isIncludedInSpecialOrder number one or number two or
isIncludedInSpecialOrder，number 是 1、2 等
whatever. If you're doing that, then you can
如果你要这样做的话，那你可以
get your own associated data using switch on self.
通过 switch self 来获取自己的关联值
Cuz I'm inside the enum implementation here, right?
因为我还在 enum 实现的内部
So I can switch on self, and then,
所以我可以对 self 进行 switch，然后
I could get my associated data out so
我能够得到个关联值
I can calculate my calories. Or
然后我就可以计算卡路里了
in this case, I'm calculating whether the hamburger with
这里我在判断一个汉堡
two patties is included in special order number two.
有两个肉饼的话是不是二号套餐
And my code here says yes because pretty much,
而我的代码会说“是的”，因为这里说
special order number one is a single burger,
一号套餐是单层汉堡
and/or number two is a double. Now there's some other
二号套餐就是双层的。现在还有些其他
interesting things to look at in this code. Notice that
有趣的地方。注意这里的代码
fries and cookie right there. Right in the middle, fries and
薯条和饼干，中间的 .fries 和 .cookie
cookie. Those I combine them into one case,
我把这两个合并为了同一个 case
which that's allowed with commas you can have multiple
这是可以的，你可以用英文逗号分隔多个
going on there. Also noticing drink, okay, I'm
不同的情况。同时看这个 .drink
getting the number of ounces in a drink but evidently in
我们知道了饮料有多少盎司。显然
a special order you can have any drink that's 16 ounces.
套餐里所有的饮料都是 16 盎司的
So I don't care what kind of drink it is, I don't care for
所以我并不在乎是什么种类的饮料，我不在意
that brand. So I use the universal i don't care symbol
brand 是什么，所以我就用了通用的“我不关心它”这个符号
in Swift which is under bar, right? Remember, we used
也就是 Swift 里的英文下划线 _，对吧？记得我们
underbar when we didn't care what the external name in
在不想要 touchCard 的实参标签时用下划线代替
touch card was. We used it in a for loop when we didn't
Concentration 在 for 循环里使用下划线
care what the identifier was anymore in concentration,
表示并不在意那个循环变量是多少
so we can use it here as well, all right?
所以我们这里也可以用，好吧？
You can modify self in an enum as long as it's in a var. If
你在枚举里是可以改变 self 的，当然它得是个 var
it's modifiable, you just say self equals some other case.
如果是可变的，你就说 self = 某个其他的 case
And if that other case requires associated data,
如果那个其他的 case 有关联值
you'll have to provide it then, you can say self equals.
你同时把它们也初始化了，这样你就可以用 self = 来改变了
Now, a very important thing to notice here, if you're going
这里有个要注意的，非常重要的是，如果你要
to modify yourself in an enum by saying self equals,
通过 self = 来更改枚举的话
that's the only way to modify yourself,
顺便说这是唯一的方法
by the way. Then you have to put mutating
你必须要用 mutating
in front of the function that mutates you,
修饰这个改变你的方法
that modifies self.
修饰这个更改 self 的方法
That's because fast enum is a value type and
这是因为枚举是值类型
remember the value types are passed around by copying but
值类型是通过拷贝传递的
there is copy on write. Swift does copy on write which
不过我们有写时复制。Swift 的写时复制意味着
means it doesn't actually make a copy until you write.
它在你改写之前并不会进行拷贝
Well if it's gonna do that,
为了能实现这个功能
it needs to know which funcs might write. So
Swift 需要知道哪些函数是会写数据的
that's what mutating means, it means this func might write,
这就是 mutating 的意思，表示这个函数可能会写数据
it might change this. You have to do exactly the same thing
可能会更改 self。在结构体里，你也要做同样的事情
in a struct. If you have a func in a struct, and
如果你的结构体里有个方法
it modifies any internal state of
它更改了任意一个结构体的内部状态
the struct, it has to be marked mutating, so
那它就必须被标为 mutating
the Swift knows to copy and write. And not to worry, Swift
这样 Swift 就能够写时复制了。不用担心，Swift
is super smart, it'll see your code, it'll see you're saying
很聪明，它会看你的代码，如果发现你说
self equal, it'll see that you're modifying your var in
self = 的话，它就知道你在更改结构体
a struct And it will complain and say this is protected you
里的变量，然后就给你抱怨说 self 是被保护的
can't write to this thing coz this is not a mutating func.
你不能更改这个内容，因为这个函数不是 mutating 的
And you can fix it by making it mutating and
你只要把它改成 mutating 就可以了
in fact you can see that concentration demo in a second
其实我们等会儿会用 Concentration 来演示下
here. All right so that's it for enums, very simple.
好，这就是枚举，很简单
So an optional then is just an enum, it looks like this,
所以其实可选类型，就是个枚举，看起来是这样的
kind of, conceptually. It's an optional,
概念上就是这样的。这就是 Optional
it's a generic type like array is. Array can have anything in
和 Array 一样的泛型。数组可以存储任何类型的元素
it, an optional can be an optional Int,
Optional 可以是可选的 Int
an optional string, whatever it's a generic type. And
可选的 String，等等，因为它是个泛型
it has two cases in the enum,
这个枚举有两种情况
the case none which is not set, nil, and the other case
case none 就是没有值，nil；另一个是 case some
some in which it has some associated data of that type.
它会有相应的关联值
So an optional int that would mean int, so that's it,
比如可选 Int 的关联值就是 Int。就是这样
that's what an optional is. Now an optional, Why don't,
这就是个可选类型。那我们为什么不能
why didn't we just leave it in enum?
就让可选作为枚举就行了呢？
Well, God, can you imagine,
哇哦，天呐，你想像一下
every time you wanna unwrap an optional, you're having to
每次你要解包可选类型的时候，你都要
switch on that thing in case some get the associated data?
用 switch 来判断是哪个 case，然后再得到关联值？
That would be so much typing. So all of these special
那我们得写很多代码。所以所有这些特殊的
characters we have are optionals, question marks,
字符，在可选类型上使用的问号
exclamation points, ifs, double question marks.
感叹号，if 的语法，?? 提供默认值等
All that stuff is just so that we don't have to be constantly
这些都是为了让我们不需要总是
switching on our optional and doing case this, case that.
用 switch 来判断可选类型然后 case 这个 case 那个的
But that's all it's doing under the covers,
但这就是它内部的实现
it's just syntactic sugar that is doing that.
这些都只是完成这些操作的语法糖
It's not doing anything else,
并没有干其他什么的
it's not, nothing special. And so I'm gonna show you what all
就是这样，没什么特别的。让我来给你们看看
these special characters look like in enum land.
用枚举而不是这些特殊字符会是什么样的
And, and I'm even gonna show you a new enum or
同时我还要给你展示个新的和枚举
a new optional thing, which is this thing at the bottom
和可选类型相关的东西，就是最底下这个
called optional chaining. And it's where you use a single
叫做可选链接（optional chaining）的。你可以用一个
question mark when you're accessing an optional.
问号来访问可选类型
Which that's the one thing we have not seen, and I'm gonna
这个是我们还没有见到的，这个我也会
show you how that works by showing you in enum land.
展示给你们看用枚举实现会是什么样的
All right? So, declaring optionals, obvious, right?
好吧？好，声明一个可选类型，很简单，对吧？
If I say hello, which is an optional string,
如果是 "hello"，那就是可选的字符串
that's just optional angle brackets string. And
那就是 Optional
remember that optionals always start out nil. So, I'm gonna,
然后记住可选类型默认值为 nil，所以我要
it's gonna start out none. Couldn't be simpler.
让其他的刚开始都是 .none，很简单
Unwrapping, also very simple, that's just switching
解包，也很简单，我就 switch
on the thing. So, if I have an optional string hello, and I
这个东西。如果我有个可选的字符串 hello，那我就
say print(hello!), exclamation point to unwrap it,
print(hello!)，感叹号强制解包
I'm just switching on hello. And if it's in the none case,
我就用 switch 判断 hello。如果是 .none 的情况的话
I crash. And if it's in the some case,
我就让程序崩溃。如果是 .some 的情况
then I print whatever the associated data is. Same thing
我就让它打印这个关联值。同样的
done with if let at the bottom there. I'm switching on hello.
下面的 if-let 也是这样。我 switch hello
If it's in the some case, I do it.
如果是 .some 的情况，我就执行它
If it's in the none case,
如果是 .none 的情况
I do the else part of the if. Everybody got that?
我就执行 else 里面的代码。大家都还听得懂吧？
Implicitly unwrapped optionals are exactly the same. It's
隐式解析的可选类型也是这样
just that when I say print hello over here on this side,
只不过我这边 print(hello) 的时候
this print hello, I don't have to put the exclamation point.
这个 print(hello) 我不需要加感叹
And it still switches on hello and crashes if it's none. So
它还是 switch 判断，是 .none 就崩溃
that's implicitly unwrapped. Those start out as nil too
这就是隐式解析。他们也默认是 nil
because they're just optionals. The nil-coalescing
毕竟它们也只是可选类型。空值合并（nil-coalescing）
operator, which is that defaulting thing we used,
运算符，我们使用过这个 ?? 来提供默认值
if you remember, in our code. We looked in our emoji
如果你还记得我们的代码的话。我们查找 emoji
dictionary, and if it wasn't there,
字典，如果里面没有的话
then we returned question mark. That's just
我们就返回个问号，这其实就是
switching on it. And if it's in the case none, then it uses
switch 判断，如果是 .none 的话，就用
the default, okay, the thing on the other side. And
默认值，?? 右边的那个
if it's in the case some, then it uses the thing it found.
如果是 .some 的情况，那就用关联值
This is optional chaining. So optional chaining, imagine
然后这个是可选链接（optional chaining）
right here, okay, if you look at this little let x equal,
你看这里，你看这个 let x =
imagine that x and the method foo and
假设 x 有 foo 这个方法（的返回值）
the var bar, all three of those, imagine those return
有 bar 这个变量。假设这三个都返回
an optional string. Okay, so we don't know what they do,
可选类型的字符串。我们不知道具体是干什么的
but they return an optional string.
但它们都是可选类型的字符串
They may or may not return nil. Okay, well, what optional
可能会，也可能不会返回 nil。好，其实
chaining there allows us to do is to call those thing,
可选链接让我们能够调用这些
things in sequence called one. And
只用一串代码。先调用一个
then when we get the value, call the next thing on that.
得到了返回值之后，再调用第二个
And we get the value, call the next thing on that. And
我们得到了之后，再调用下一个
if at any time any of those things is nil, we just bail
如果其中任何一个环节返回了 nil，我们就马上结束
out and return nil. So the way that works in optional land is
然后返回 nil。而这用 Optional 枚举写就是
we switch on that first. If it's none, we return nil.
我们 switch 判断第一个，如果是 .none 就返回 nil
But if it's not, we get the data and call foo.
如果不是的话，我们就那关联值调用 foo
If that works, we get the, that data from foo, and
如果可行的话，我们从 foo 得到数据
we call bar. And then eventually,
我们调用 bar。最终
we set y equal to z that comes out of that, right?
我们把 y 赋值为结果 z，好吧？
We're just moving across the chain. If, at any time,
我们只是沿着链条走。如果任何时候
any of those things is nil, look at all the case nones.
其中任何一个是 nil 的话，你看看这些 case .none
Case .none, case .none, case .none, y gets to be nil, and
case .none, case .none, case .none，y 都是 nil
we're done and move along. Okay, so that's optional
然后就完成了，接着执行下一条。好，这就是可选链接
chaining. I made it optional, no pun intended, for
我让你可选，这并不是双关，你可以
you to read about that in your current assignment.
选择在现在的作业里阅读这个部分
I recommend you do because you can make really beautiful code
我建议你读一读，因为你能写出优雅的代码
using optional chaining. It's really nice.
可选链接非常的好用
Okay, so we're gonna finish up today with a little review and
好，我们今天最后来复习
a look forward to the data structures to use to build
然后预习下写 Swift 程序用到的
an app in Swift. These are the four, class,
数据结构一共有四个，类
struct, enum, and protocol. Protocol is the new one that
结构体、枚举、和协议（protocol）。协议是个新的内容
I'm gonna talk about starting on Wednesday. So a class,
这个我周三会讲。所以，一个类
as we know, supports an object-oriented design.
我们知道，支持面向对象的设计
It has single inheritance of both functionality and data.
它是单一继承功能和数据
You inherit the data, your vars.
你继承了所有的数据，变量
Stored vars get inherited, um, as well as all your methods
继承了存储变量，同时还有方法
and stuff. It's a reference type, lives in the heap.
这些。它是引用类型，存在堆里
Now one thing we didn't talk about, though,
但我们又一个没有讲的是
this class lives in the heap. When does it get cleaned up
这些类都在堆里，但它什么时候被释放
out of the heap? And how does that happen? Okay, so yeah, so
离开堆呢？那是怎么发生的呢？是的
if, people who are coming from Java, you're probably like,
学过 Java 的人，多半会想
oh, garbage collection maybe? Okay, um, but no, okay,
哦，大概就是 Garbage Collection？其实不是
Swift does not use garbage collection.
Swift 不用垃圾回收
It uses a very awesome system called reference counting. And
它采用的是个很棒的引用计数系统，更准确的说是
in fact, it's automatic reference counting,
自动引用计数（Automatic Reference Counting，ARC）
it's all handled for you. So how does reference counting
它会帮你把一切都处理了。那引用计数是怎么回事呢？
work? Okay, we need to talk a little bit about that.
这个我们需要讲一讲
So let's take a little detour here. By the way, examples of
让我们来讲讲这个题外话。顺便一提
classes that we've seen of course are UI view controller,
我们看到的类的例子是 UIViewController
view controller, which is our subclass of it, UI button,
我们 ViewController 是继承它的子类，UIButton
UI label, concentration, we made that a class. Those
UILabel，我们自己写的 Concentration。这些
are all classes, not structs, right? All right, so let's
都是类，不是结构体，好吧？好，让我们
talk about how this automatic reference counting thing
来讲讲自动引用计数是怎么工作的
works. It's really simple, every time, somehow magically,
它其实非常简单。每次，很神奇的
every time that you create a pointer to a reference type in
每次你创建一个到堆里引用类型的指针
the heap, Swift adds one to some counter somewhere. And
Swift 就会把某处的计数器加一
every time that pointer to it goes out of scope or
每当有指针的作用域结束了
is not pointed to it anymore, like it was an optional,
或者不再指向某个对象的时候，就好像可选类型
it got set to nil, for example,
变为 nil 了一样，打个比方就是这样
then it decrements that count. And when that count goes to 0,
Swift 就会把记录减一。当这个数变为 0 之后
it takes it out of the heap instantly. It's not like
它马上就会离开堆。并不像是
it's keeping track, and it's doing any marking and
它会去监视，然后做标记
sweeping, like a garbage collection. It actually
换内存，并不会像 GC 这样做。它其实会
instantly removes it as soon as no one points to it. So
只要没人指向它就立刻把它移除
it couldn't be simpler, it's exact way you would think,
不能再简单了，和你预想的一样
conceptually, to make it work.
概念上它就是这样的
It's actually quite difficult under the covers to do that.
其实它背后的实现还挺复杂的
Swift was designed with it in mind from start.
Swift 从一开始设计的时候就考虑到了 ARC
So it's an awesome system. You can influence
这是个很好的系统。你是可以稍微影响
this automatic reference counting a little bit.
自动引用计数的过程的
You can't really control it, but you can influence,
你并不能控制它，但你可以影响它
with these three key words when you declare a var,
在声明变量的时候用这三个关键字中的一个
okay, a strong, weak, and unowned.
分别是 strong、weak 和 unowned
These are the three kind of influencers you can do.
这是你能影响它的三种方式
The first one, strong, is normal reference counting.
第一个 strong 是普通的引用计数
So that just means if there's a, this pointer is strong, and
意思就是，这是一个强引用的指针
so keep that thing in the heap as long as this is around,
只要我这个变量还在就把那个对象留在堆里
because I need it, I'm pointing to it.
因为我指向了它，我还需要它
That's the default.
这是默认的行为
So, we never actually type the keyword strong.
所以我们从来不用 strong（注：也不是关键字）
It's the default. It's always there.
这是默认的，总是会在那里
It's kind of like internal with that access control.
就好像 internal 这个访问级别一样
We don't actually ever type that.
我们从来不把它写出来
Now weak, you've actually seen before. You all remember weak?
然后是 weak。你其实之前已经见到过了，你们还记得 weak 吗？
It was on the outlets. Okay,
@IBOutlet 就是弱引用的
when we made that outlet connection, I said oh,
当我们连接出口的时候，我说过
that, see that weak? I'm gonna tell you about that next week.
看到那个 weak 了吗？我下周给你讲
Well, I'm living up to my promise, I'm telling you about
这不，我遵守了我的诺言，我现在给你讲
weak. What does weak mean? Weak means I'm
weak。weak 是什么意思？弱引用表示我
pointing to this thing in the heap, but I'm only really
指向堆里的这个对象，但我只会
interested in it if someone else is interested in it.
在别人也对它感兴趣的时候才感兴趣
In other words, if someone else has a strong pointer to
换句话说，如果别人有一个到它的强引用
it, keep it in the heap. But as soon as no one else is
就把它留在堆里。但只要其他人都对它
interested in this, in other words,
不感兴趣了，也就是
all other strong pointers go away. Set me to nil and
所有其他的强引用都没了，就把我这个设为 nil
throw the thing out of the heap. So this is the don't
然后把它从堆中释放。所以这就是
keep that thing in the heap on my account kind of pointer.
“不要因为我而把它留在堆里”这种指针
And notice that it gets set to nil if all the other strong
然后注意它会被设为 nil，当其他强引用
pointers go away. So what kind of type does this have to be?
都没了的话设为 nil。那这个变量的类型必须是什么？
It has to be an optional.
它必须要是可选类型
So this weak only works with optional pointers to
所以 weak 来弱引用只适用于可选类型的
reference types, okay, things that are in the heap,
指向堆里的引用类型对象的指针
which our outlets are. If you remember our outlets,
就比如我们的出口变量。如果你还记得那些 @IBOutlet
like flip count label was a UI label exclamation point. That
比如 flipCountLabel 是个 UILabel!
was an implicitly unwrapped optional. It was an optional,
这是隐式解析的可选类型，它是可选类型的
right? Same thing card buttons was an implicitly unwrapped
对吧？同样的，cardButtons 是隐式解析的
optional. So those pointers to things in the UI.
可选类型，所以弱引用的指针指向 UI 里的内容
If for some reason those things left the UI, okay,
如果这些控件因为某种原因离开了用户界面
got removed from the UI somehow, which is possible,
被从 UI 上移除了，这确实可能发生
but rare. Then those things would get set to nil, okay?
虽然很少见，但这时它们就会被设为 nil，好吧？
And you would no longer be pointing to them,
你也不会再引用它们
and that's what they want.
这也是他们想要的效果
Because if there's no flip count label,
因为如果没有 flipCountLabel
there's no use trying to update it. So
那就不用尝试去更新它
that's why they make those weak All right, now, weak,
这就是为什么这些 UI 控件都是 weak 引用。总之，weak
there's only a couple of places that we use weak
我们只有几个地方会常用弱引用
commonly. One is for outlets, another one is for delegation.
其中之一就是 @IBOutlet 出口，另一个是代理
Remember back to my MVC talk, I talked about the delegation,
还记得我之前讲 MVC，我谈到了委托代理
the data source. And we have these pointers from the view
数据源，然后我们这些从视图
back to the controller where there's that blind and
指回控制器的匿名的
structure of communication all that,
标准化的通讯这些
which I'm gonna talk about on Wednesday.
就是我周三讲的
Those pointers are weak, because the view,
那些指针都是弱引用，因为视图
if the thing that they're sending will did and
如果它们发送这些 will、did
should to goes away, well, they're not gonna send those
should 去的目标对象不在了，那视图就不用再发送
messages anymore, so they want to be nil, okay. There's no
这些消息了，所以它们要是能够为 nil 的。没有
one to send their messages to then they just want to be nil,
人需要发送消息给它，那我们就希望它是 nil
okay. They don't want to be pointed to something.
这个变量就不希望指向任何东西
They certainly don't want a thing it points to,
视图肯定不希望因为它的引用的对象
to get stuck in the heap because of it.
因为这些引用而被困在堆里
Because they're happy to just not send the messages if
因为它们很乐意就不发消息
that thing wants to leave the heap, otherwise we don't
如果它们要离开堆就离开吧。其他时候我们一般
use weak that much. Okay, last is unowned.
不会怎么使用 weak。最后是 unowned
Unowned is don't reference count this,
无主引用是就不把它算到引用计数里
in other words I'm pointing to something in the heap, but
换句话说我引用了堆里的某个对象，但是
don't count it as a strong pointer. And I promise I'll
不要把它算作强引用。我保证我
never access this thing when it's gone from the heap. Now,
从来不会在这个对象释放之后再使用它
this is very dangerous, this is basically trying to
这个是非常危险的，这基本就是尝试
outsmart the automatic reference counting system.
证明自己比自动引用计数更厉害
You're saying, you know when it's in the heap or not, and
你在说我清楚的知道这对象是否在堆里
this is really rare. And the way,
这种情况是很少见的
the one time we use this is to avoid a memory cycle, okay.
我们唯一一种情况是用来避免引用循环
Everyone know what a memory cycle is,
大家都知道引用循环是什么？
that's where you have something in the heap and
那是你有个在堆里的对象
it points to something else in the heap, and
它引用了堆里的另一个对象
that thing points back to it.
然后那另一个对象又引用了回来
So, they're pointing to each other, keeping each other in
这样它们就相互引用，把对方留在
the heap. But no one else is interested in them. No one
堆里。但其他人对它们都不感兴趣了
points to either of them. They only just point to each other.
其他人并没有指向它们中的任何一个，只有它们互相引用
So they're just sitting in the heap for no reason.
它们就这样无缘无故地留在了堆里
No one's even accessing them, that's a memory cycle. And
其他人都不会访问它们，这就是引用循环
memory cycles aren't generally created in Swift normally but
Swift 里一般不会有引用循环
there's one way they're easy to create which is
但是有一种方法我们能够简单地创建一个
closures, okay.
那就是闭包
Which is a feature I'm gonna talk about on Wednesday, okay.
这是我周三要讲的特性
And so we will use unowned with closures. All right,
所以我们会在闭包里使用无主引用。好
back to our list of data structures here, of course
我们回到这个数据结构列表。当然
there's struct we know all about that. It's a value type,
我们知道了关于结构体的全部内容，它是值类型
it's copy on write, there's no inheritance of data.
它会在写时复制，不存在继承
But you're gonna learn with protocols there is inheritance
但你会学到可以通过 protocol，用协议来继承
of functionality,
功能
in fact multiple inheritance of functionality. And you've
更准确的说是功能的多重继承。你也已经
seen examples of struct cards, dictionary, string, character,
看到过很多结构体的例子了，Card, Dictionary, String, Character
int, double, UInt32, lots of structs have happened
Int, Double, UInt32 等等这些结构体都在这里
there. And I have here, let's jump over to concentrations
然后我们这里有，让我们到 Concentration 里
see what happens when we make concentration of struct.
看看我们把 Concentration 改为 struct 会发生什么
How about
要不
I start off the next one with that because we're pretty much
我们下节课开始再讲这个，因为我们已经基本上
out of time here. Enum, I'm not going to,
没有时间了。枚举，我不准备
oh yes, this is the demo, which I will do next time. And
哦，这是个演示，我下节课再来展示
then enum here we already just covered, so I'm not going to
然后枚举我们刚刚才讲完，我不准备
talk about it, another value type, discrete values. It also
再讲一遍，这就是另外一种值类型，有不同的值。它还
can have inherit the same kind of functionality inheritance.
可以继承功能
This functionality inheritance that I keep kind of mentioning
这个我一直在提到的功能的继承
is done using this last one, which is called protocols.
是通过最后一个 protocol 来实现的
So I'm gonna start off on Wednesday with a detailed
所以我周三回开始细讲
explanation of what a protocol is.
协议是什么
It's fundamental to the design of all of foundation,
它是所有基础的设计模式
all the array, dictionary, string, int.
所有的 Array, Dictionary, String, Int
And all of those things fundamentally using protocols
所有这些基础的内容都用到了 protocol
everywhere, massive number of protocols.
到处都是，大量的协议
And it's also fundamental with things like delegation and
同时这也是委托代理模式的基础
stuff like that, so it's very, very important. And to round
就像这样的内容，非常非常重要。这让我们能
out our full understanding of how to build data structures
完整地了解如何在 Swift 里构建数据结构
in Swift. Okay, so we'll start off on Wednesday with that and
我们星期三会先讲这些
I will see you then. >> For more,
到时候再见。>> 更多课程
please visit us at stanford.edu.
详见 stanford.edu